<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first pinciples [sic] of the doctrine of Christ together with stronger meat for them that are skil'd in the word of righteousness, or, the doctrine of living unto God, wherein the body of divinity is briefly and methodically handled by way of question and answer / published at the desire and for the use of the Church of Christ in Norwich in New-England by James Fitch.</title>
            <author>Fitch, James, 1622-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11209841</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11209841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:73)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first pinciples [sic] of the doctrine of Christ together with stronger meat for them that are skil'd in the word of righteousness, or, the doctrine of living unto God, wherein the body of divinity is briefly and methodically handled by way of question and answer / published at the desire and for the use of the Church of Christ in Norwich in New-England by James Fitch.</title>
                  <author>Fitch, James, 1622-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 76, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Foster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Increase Mather.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>The firſt Pinciples of the Doctrine of</hi> CHRIST; Together with ſtronger Meat for them that are skil'd in the Word of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR The Doctrine of living unto God, wherein the</hi> Body of Divinity <hi>Is Briefly and methodically handled by way of</hi> Queſtion <hi>and</hi> Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the deſire, and for the uſe of the Church of Chriſt in</hi> Norwich <hi>in</hi> NEW-ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JAMES FITCH <hi>Paſtor of that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 11.</bibl>
               <p>Come ye Children, hearken unto me, I will teach you the fear of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13.</bibl>
               <p>Hold faſt the form of ſound words which thou haſt heard of me, in Faith and Love which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Boſton, <hi>Printed by</hi> John Foſter. 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>COncerning the Neceſſity and Antiquity of that great Ordinance of <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> (which is a plain laying down of the Principles of the Oracles of God) there are many that have written. Nor was ever any man that had the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plane tibi perſuaſum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe oportet, Eccleſiam Dei Catecheſi carere non poſſe.</hi> Calvinus <hi>in Epiſt. Protect. Angliae.</hi>
               </note> true fear of God planted in his heart, or that had a ſenſe of the worth of ſouls (if indeed the care of ſouls hath been committed to him) altogether neglective as to the practice of ſo great and neceſſary a duty. Abraham <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> thoſe that were born in his houſe. The Lord commanded his People of old that they ſhould be diligent in teaching their Children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 7. The Hebrew word there uſed (as is <note place="margin">v. <hi>Paraei Prolog. in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſini Catech.</hi>
               </note> commonly and truly obſerved) ſignifieth to <hi>whet;</hi> ſo are the ſame precepts and principles to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated even over and over again, as the knife upon the whetſtone. Solomon ſpeaketh much concerning the advantage he received in that he was well principled by his father in his tender years. And the Jews to this Day, although they have loſt the power of Religion for above theſe 1600 years, yet keep up ſomething of the form of it, being very carefull to inſtruct their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Principles of the Jewiſh Religion.
<pb facs="tcp:46814:3"/> They have their <hi>Catechiſms,</hi> in ſpecial that of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hotting. de jure Hebraeor. Buxtorf. Synag. Iud Cap.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>R Levi,</hi> much commended by ſome Chriſtian Writers. And <hi>Buxtorf</hi> (who as to the Jewiſh Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities is eſteemed the moſt learned Writer that the world hath known) giveth us a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of theſe matters, how the Jews have been wont to teach their children ſome ſelect places of Scripture as ſoon as ever they can ſpeak, and by that time they are thirteen years of age, they are able to give an account concerning their ſix hundred and thirteen precepts, which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the ſum of the Moſaical Law. And ſhall Chriſtians come ſhort of Jews, reſpecting dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in a Religious Education of their Children? Thoſe ſix Principles mentioned by Paul, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1, 2. are by ſome called <hi>Catechiſmus Apoſtoli,</hi> the <note place="margin">Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgenſes</note> Apoſtles Catechiſm, as ſuppoſing that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did reduce the Sum of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe ſix heads. I ſhall not ſubſcribe to that Notion; for I conceive (with due reſpect to Interpreters that have thought otherwiſe) that the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt there mentioned, are ſuch Principles in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity <note place="margin">Jacobus Cappellus in locum.</note> as are owned by the Jews in common with Chriſtians, who believe there muſt be Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from dead works, and Faith towards God, (albeit they deny Faith in Chriſt) and they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Reſurrection from the dead, and eternal Judgement, and alſo the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms, &amp; of the laying on of hands. Nevertheleſs, it is certain that the Apoſtles did feed their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with Milk as well as with ſtrong meat. <hi>Egeſippus</hi> relateth that by virtue of <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> all the Kingdoms in the then known world; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an alteration as to their heatheniſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, within forty years after Chriſts aſcenſion.
<pb facs="tcp:46814:3"/> Nor were the famous Teachers in the Chriſtian Church, who flouriſhed in the Ages neer to the Apoſtles, aſhamed to be called <hi>Catechiſts. Opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> was a <hi>Catechiſt</hi> at <hi>Carthage; Origen</hi> at <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> had his <hi>Paedagogus; Lactantius</hi> his <hi>Inſtitutions;</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> his Tract <hi>de Catechizandis Rudibus. Euſebius</hi> reports that of old one was ſet apart on purpoſe for this work, in the primitive Churches, who did bear the name of <hi>The Catechiſt.</hi> It is true that thoſe Primitive Catechiſts did not (all of them) inſtruct their Auditors by way of Queſtion and Anſwer, only they cauſed the Truth reſpecting the main <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kata</hi> &amp; <hi>echeo</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſono.</note> Principles in Religion to be often reſounding &amp; <hi>Ecchoing</hi> (according to the Notation of the word <hi>Catechize)</hi> in the ears of thoſe that were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by them, yet had they of old, a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar day appointed, when thoſe that had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed were examined concerning their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency. And that form of procedure by way of <note place="margin">Pelargus.</note> Queſtion and Anſwer, was obſerved by <hi>Iunilius,</hi> who lived Anno 545. And it is a courſe that doth neceſſitate the Auditor to attend and profit. When Sermons are preached, men are ſinfully apt to ſleep and wander, which under this way of Catechiſing they cannot eaſily doe. This Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucer de vera Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. recon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cil. Sr. Edw. Sandys.</hi> 88. &amp; <hi>Dr Andrews.</hi>
               </note> was indeed in a manner loſt (both name and thing,) as <hi>Bucer</hi> teſtifies, when Popiſh Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian darkneſs covered the earth, but (as a worthy Perſon in his <hi>Speculum Europae</hi> hath well obſerved) the firſt Reformers by diligence in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing,</hi> cauſed the light of the Goſpel to ſpread and prevail wonderfully. Yea the Authors of the <hi>Tridentine Catechiſm</hi> complain that it was ſo. Whence the Papiſts have in policy ſet up a courſe of inſtructing Children in the deſtructive Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <note place="margin">in Praefat</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:4"/> of their Religion, as hoping thereby to out-doe the Proteſtants, who by their <hi>Catechiſms</hi> had gained ſo much ground above an hundred years ago. Moreover, by diligence in this way, the Truth of the Goſpel hath been preſerved as well as propagated. Thus purity of Doctrine ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively continued amongſt the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to Generation. When certain Juſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites were ſent amongſt them with a deſign to corrupt their Children, they could not doe it, becauſe they had received contrary Principles of Truth, from thoſe, under whoſe nurture and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition they had been educated; ſo that the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites returned with amazement, profeſſing that among the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> Children of ſeven years old underſtood more in the Scriptures, and in the matters of Religion, then could be ſaid of many of their learned men. And experience doth ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirm the truth of this, inaſmuch as they that embrace Hereſyes of this or that kind, have (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them) been found wofully ignorant as to Fundamentals in the Doctrine of Chriſt, ſo <note place="margin">Principia ſunt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titate, maxima virtute.</note> that the reaſon of their being ſo ſeduced is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they never throughly learned and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their Catechiſms: of ſo great concernment is it to be well grounded in Principles.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt Ages have abounded in labours of this kind; one ſpeaketh of no leſs then five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Catechiſms extant: which of theſe is moſt elegible, I ſhall leave unto others to determine. I ſuppoſe there is no particular Catechiſm, of <note place="margin">v. Mr. Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lip Nye Beams of former Light.</note> which it may be ſaid, it is the beſt for every Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, or for every Congregation. Nevertheleſs it muſt needs be acknowledged, that thoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels of Divinity (whether Catechiſtically com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed or otherwiſe) wherein Scriptural Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Diſtributions, expreſſing the Sum of
<pb facs="tcp:46814:4"/> the only true Chriſtian Religion, are methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally diſpoſed, according to the golden Rules of Art, have a peculiar excellency and uſefulneſs attending them. In this way that great and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Martyr of France, <hi>Peter Ramus</hi> held forth the light to others. After him ſucceeded the profoundly learned and godly, <hi>Alexander Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſon,</hi> of whom Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> was wont to ſay, that the Lord would not ſuffer <hi>Richardſon</hi> to live unto old age, or to finiſh what was in his heart &amp; head to doe, for the ſame reaſon that he would not permit more then three hundred Souldiers to goe with Gideon, even leſt the Engliſh Nation ſhould glory too much in their own ſtrength, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a mighty man was once theirs. Mr. <hi>Yates</hi> his Model of Divinity, Catechiſtically com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, (a very profitable Book) is as to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, definitions, &amp; diſtributions, wholly <hi>Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and a great part of his explications alſo, ſo far as they are ſolid and demonſtrative. A ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Reader may eaſily perceive which are <hi>Richardſons</hi> and which <hi>Yates</hi> his Notions, though in the Book it is not mentioned. About the ſame time the Lord raiſed up that great Champion, Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> of whom one too truly complaineth, that there might be written over his Grave as once over <hi>Scipio</hi>'s, <hi>Ingrata Patria, ne oſſa mea qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem habes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mr. Jeanes.</note> He in his <hi>Medulla Theologiae</hi> hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved <hi>Richardſons</hi> method and Principles to great advantage. And truly I concur with that worthy Divine, who ſaid, that <hi>next to the Bible, he eſteemed</hi> Dr. Ames <hi>his Marrow of Divinity as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. Thom. Goodwin.</note> 
               <hi>the beſt Book in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, the Reader may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and will undoubtedly find, that which will be well worth his ſerious peruſal in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:46814:5"/> Catechiſm. As for the worthy Author, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lord hath ſeen meet to fix his preſent ſtation not only in a wilderneſs, but in one of the obſcureſt places therein, yet is his praiſe in the Goſpel throughout all the Churches. And by what is here preſented, (as well as by other things formerly publiſhed) it doth appear that the Author is a Workman that needeth not to be aſhamed. For here is not only Milk for Babes in reſpect of Principles, with much ſolid dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aſſerted; but ſtrong Meat in reſpect of rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal explications, and Demonſtrations of thoſe Principles, that the ableſt men, who have their ſenſes exerciſed in diſcerning things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may be edified. <hi>Luther</hi> did profeſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be <hi>Diſcipulus Catechiſmi,</hi> a Learner of his Catechiſm, all his dayes. The work then of a <hi>Catechist</hi> is not unbecoming or unſuitable to the ableſt Teachers. And if endeavours of this ſort were more diligently attended, it would be one good means to prevent Degeneracy in the ſucceeding Generation.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord bleſs this faithfull undertaking for that end, and grant that the earth may be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Boſton.</hi> 
                  <date>4. <hi>m.</hi> 23. <hi>d.</hi> 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>INCREASE MATHER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:6"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46814:6"/>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> WHat is Religion?</head>
               <p>A. Religion is a Doctrine of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto God, and conſiſts of two parts, Faith and Obſervance.</p>
               <p>The thing defined is Religion, it may be called Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, as it cometh from God, and leadeth to God, and to a divine life, and ſome have thought it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Religion by occaſion of mans fall, man at firſt was bound to God, but he by his ſin looſened himſelf, and by the Rule of Religion he is bound again; Religion is a word compounded of <hi>re</hi> and <hi>ligo</hi> to bind again, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
               <p>Religion is] for if there were no Religion none could be irreligious, if no Law then no tranſgreſſion, many ſeem to be Religious, few are indeed Religious, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 26, 27.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Definition it ſelf.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The general nature and Doctrine] Religion may be called an Art, as it conſiſts of Precepts, breathing the firſt and trueſt knowledge by which man is guided to his end, but it's called a Doctrine, becauſe none can learn it but thoſe who are taught of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. None can learn it by the book of nature, for there are ſome leſſons in Religion which are not to be found in the book of Creation, (namely) mans <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Anastaſie,</hi> how man at firſt did fall, and how he is reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Chriſt, and the book of nature is blurred by mans ſin, the curſe is fallen upon the works of Creation, and thus this book is darkened.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This can not be learnt only by humane induſtry, for man by nature is void of ſpiritual eye-ſight, <hi>Re.</hi> 3. 18. hence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46814:7"/> Religion is called a Doctrine as it is taught of God.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By giving the Rule from Heaven, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 2.</item>
                  <item>2. By the illumination of the Spirit of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 13, 14.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſpecial nature of Religion appears in the end and proper object of it.</p>
               <p>Of living unto God,] to live unto God is the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent kind of life, hence it is an act of the moſt noble faculty, upon the moſt excellent object, in the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent manner, and therefore hath religion, which is the moſt excellent Rule to lead to this life.</p>
               <p>It is not Reaſon, nor ſpeech, nor quantity, nor nature, can be the proper object of Religion, all theſe have their proper acts and Rules to guide them, but it's goodneſs it ſelf which is the proper Object and end of Divinity.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Man was made for God.</item>
                  <item>2. Hence he ought to live unto God.</item>
                  <item>3. Hence he ought to be fitted for this end.</item>
                  <item>4. This is his goodneſs, and to this Religion leads him, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 3. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 6.</item>
               </list>
               <p>[The parts of Religion are Faith and Obſervance.]</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are parts, for they have a common affection to the whole, and are diſtinct one from another, he that is Religious hath both theſe, and yet Faith is not obſervance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are integral parts, give being to the whole, as Soul and body make up the man, ſo Faith and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance do make a man truly and ſufficiently Religious, for to live unto God is the end of Religion, and to this is neceſſary firſt, a principle of life, and this is Faith:</p>
               <p n="2">2. The acting of that Principle in obſervance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence Faith and Obſervance differ in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, otherwiſe they could not be parts, and in their precepts, otherwiſe they could not differ in their natures and hence the Rule of Faith is not the Rule of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance,
<pb facs="tcp:46814:7"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:8"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46814:8"/> and hence this Faith is not required in the Law, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. but concerning this more fully in that which followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Q. What is Faith?</head>
               <p>A. Faith is the firſt part of Religion, and is a truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God for life, proceeding from a grounded know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, as he hath made known himſelf in his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, and in his efficiency.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. This Faith is the firſt part of Religion, becauſe to live unto God, a principle of life, is firſtly neceſſary, and this is Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſpecial nature of this appeareth.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. A truſting in God] called a reſting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 7. a ſtaying upon God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50. 10. a looking to God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For life,] <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 20. and thus this Faith is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht firſt from Hiſtorical Faith, which is an aſſent to the Truth of the Word of God,—2dly, from tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Faith, which is a truſting for temporary things,</p>
               <p n="3">3. From miraculous Faith which is a truſting for a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous power, theſe do not come to God for life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 40. Proceeding from a grounded knowledge of God] for there can be no deſire of an unknown God, no believing on him whom we do not know, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 10. hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>1. This Faith is wrought by knowledge, 2. Hence it is not knowledge nor properly any virtue of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, life it ſelf is its Object, hence happineſs and goodneſs it ſelf, and this is properly the Object of the will, 3dly, Hence this Faith is ſeated in the will.</p>
               <p>And thus this Faith is diſtinguiſht from Fait'—in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, there we conſider the framing and making of it, here the general act and uſe of it, 2dly, Hence diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht from Faith required in the Law, the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, there Faith looketh to God as the rewarder of them who do well and live unto him,—here it looketh to God as the author of life, and of a principle of well doing;</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46814:9"/> 4. As God hath made known himſelf in his ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and in his efficiency,] for Faith apprehends in the way of Reaſon ſuch a portion of the beams and glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of God as are ſufficient to make a believer live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Faith apprehends in the way of Reaſon, for God hath made man a reaſonable Creature, hence he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands in the way of Reaſon,—hence Faith apprehends by Reaſon, otherwiſe man ſhould go without his guide, and ſee without his eye ſight, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Job.</hi> 40. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A portion of the beams of God, not the Sun it ſelf, not as God is in himſelf,, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6. 16. <hi>Job.</hi> 26. 14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So much as is ſufficient to make a believer live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 19, 20.—hence it followeth,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The act of Faith is higher then the act of Reaſon, for Reaſon in man acts upon and is converſant about, only that Reaſon which ſhineth in divine Truth, but Faith is taken up with looking upon the divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence Reaſon in a believer is a means to let in a light and good beyond Reaſon, that as the ſenſes are means to preſent the Reaſon in things to the Reaſon of man, although Reaſon is above Senſe, ſo Reaſon is a means to preſent a divine good unto Faith, though that divine good is above Reaſon, but as Reaſon can uſe the <hi>Prattomenon</hi> of the Rule of Senſe, (namely) that which is effected by it, ſo Faith can uſe the <hi>Prattomenon</hi> of the Rule of Reaſon, that which is effected by it, and yet theſe are diſtinct arts, and have diſtinct Objects, and diſtinct lights</p>
               <p>And that which God hath made known of himſelf is in his ſufficiency, and in his efficiency, for more we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee and live, and more we need not ſee and live, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 21. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 19, 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. What is the ſufficiency of God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſufficiency of God is that whereby he hath
<pb facs="tcp:46814:9"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:10"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:46814:10"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nough in himſelf, for himſelf, and more then enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or us, which conſiſts in his Eſſence, and Subſiſtence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He hath enough] otherwiſe there would be a want in him, which can not be, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In himſelf, for himſelf,] otherwiſe he could not be happy in himſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. More then enough for us,] 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 20. he hath enough for himſelf, as he is an Infinite Being, and therefore more then enough for us who are finite beings</p>
               <p>His ſufficiency conſiſts in his Eſſence, and Subſiſtence,</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Eſſence, that is his Being abſolutely conſidered.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Subſiſtence, that is, his ſtanding under ſome manner of Being, of theſe two, Reaſon may conceive, but beyond theſe Reaſon can not imagine, of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of any thing, firſt, what belongs to the Eſſence and Being as ſuch, <hi>2dly,</hi> what belongs to the Eſſence beſides its Being, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 30.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. What is the Eſſence of God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Eſſence of God is that whereby God is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely the firſt Being, and doth not exſiſt of cauſes, nor conſiſt of parts, and his Being is abſolutely pure without compoſition, and is made known to us by his divine Attributes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. There is a Being, he that denyeth that, doth deny his own Being, and makes a nothing of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                  <item>2. Being is either firſt, or ariſing from the firſt, ſo that there is a firſt Being, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43. 10, 11.</item>
                  <item>3. Abſolutely the firſt Being, therefore no cauſes of his Being</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. No efficient cauſes of his Being,</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>hence</head>
                        <item>not created cannot be annihilated.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>and hence</head>
                        <item>Independent and Supream</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item n="2">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46814:11"/> 2. No material cauſe of his being, hence inviſible and impalpable.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. No formal cauſe of his Being, hence Ingenerable and Incorruptible.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. No final cauſe of his Being, hence no art to guide him to his end, and thus he doth not exſiſt of cauſes.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And hence it followeth, he is not an integrum or intire thing made up of members, nor part of any entire thing.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="2">2. No genus or general nature exſiſting in ſpecies, nor ſpecial kind of being, for theſe imply matter and form, and thus he doth not conſiſt of parts.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. And hence he hath not Accidents or Adjuncts, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from matter or form, hence he is firſt without quantity, and hence no augmentation, nor diminution.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. Without qualities ariſing from the form acting upon the matter, hence immutable without paſſion, or ſuffering, and unreſiſtible.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And thus he is far above all our Logick and Reaſon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He hath made known himſelf by his divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, what ever is excellent being attributed to him in an eminent and inconceivable manner, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 35, 36.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. What are the divine Attributes?</head>
               <p>Anſw. They are as they are in God that one moſt pure Eſſence, but diverſly appearing to us.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. His Eſſence is pure without any compoſition, as we heard before.</item>
                  <item>2. Hence whatever is in God is God himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44. 8.</item>
                  <item>3. Hence his divine Attributes are God himſelf.</item>
                  <item>4. Hence he hath theſe not by participation, but he is every perfection it ſelf, he is wiſdome it ſelf, holineſs it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Hence he hath theſe in the higheſt degree, they can not be augmented nor diminiſhed in him.</item>
                  <item>6. Hence they are equal as they are in him, not more
<pb facs="tcp:46814:11"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46814:12"/>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46814:12"/> of one divine Attribute then of another, for they are God himſelf.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But theſe do diverſly appear to us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By different effects, as the ſame Sun ſoftens ſome things, and hardeneth other things, ſo God hath mercy on ſome, and hardeneth others, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 18. we attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Sun a ſoftening and a hardening power, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the various effects it hath upon things, ſo we attribute mercy or juſtice to God according as he ſaves ſome, or puniſheth others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By arguments in the glaſs of our Reaſon the divine Attributes appear diverſe, for we underſtand by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that ever implies, 1. That which argueth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which is argued. And thus we apprehend concerning God, as if he were the Subject of his divine Attributes, and they as Adjuncts, and thus, as if they were diſtinct from his Eſſence, and one from another, but this is improper, and we ought to believe that the divine Attributes are one with the Eſſence, and one with another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. How is God made known to us by his divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes?</head>
               <p>Anſw. God is made known to us by his divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to be one Infinite and Eternal Spirit, having life in and of himſelf, having moſt perfect underſtanding and will, and is infinitely more glorious then any Spirit, and is perfection and bleſſedneſs it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We ought to attribute the moſt excellent kind of being, and the moſt excellent properties of Being unto God, in the moſt eminent manner.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The moſt excellent kind of Being.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A living Being is the moſt excellent, Attribute Life unto him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 40.</item>
                  <item>2. A Spirit is the moſt excellent of living Beings, attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute that kind of Being to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.</item>
                  <item>3. But we muſt attribute theſe to him in an eminent manner.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:46814:13"/>
                  <item>1. Life of him, he is the Fountain of Life.</item>
                  <item>2. All kinds of life are of and in him eminently, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84. 8, 9, 10.</item>
                  <item>3. His Life and Being are one, not firſt a Being, and afterwards a living Being,—hence Infinitely more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then any Spirit whatſoever.</item>
               </list>
               <p>We ought to attribute the moſt excellent Properties of Being to him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The moſt excellent quantity, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 3. hence</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Vnity abſolutely one, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 4.</item>
                  <item>2. Infiniteneſs, without limits of Eſſence, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40. 12, hence, 1. Immenſe not meaſurable, <hi>Job.</hi> 11. 8. hence</item>
               </list>
               <p n="2">2. Incomprehenſible in place, not included nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 7, 8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Eternity, without beginning or end. 1. No time to come with him, for then he ſhould be limited to time paſt and preſent. 2. No time paſt with him, for then he ſhould be limited to time preſent and to come.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence they are one with him, for he can not be more ancient, then himſelf, and there can be no Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in Eternity, where there is no beginning nor end, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Attribute the moſt excellent qualities to him</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Moſt excellent faculties, underſtanding and will.</item>
                  <item>2. Moſt excellent virtues, Intellectual and Moral.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And theſe to be attributed in the moſt eminent manner, hence, the Attributes of greatneſs are to be attributed to the Attributes of Goodneſs, he is Infinitely and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally wiſe, holy, juſt, merciful, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 147. 5. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6. 3.</p>
               <p>And here ſhineth his happineſs, who by his perfect underſtanding doth comprehend the moſt ſovereign Truth, and with a moſt perfect will imbraceth the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt good, and is not only happy, but is perfection and happineſs it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Quest. What is the Subſiſtence of God?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:14"/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:46814:14"/> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Subſiſtence of God is that whereby the firſt Being reflecting upon himſelf ſtands under divers mutual reſpects, and diſtinct manners of Being, which are only one, in reſpect of the Eſſence, and yet are diſtinct from the Eſſence, and one from another,</p>
               <p>1. The firſt Being reflecting upon himſelf] for God who is the firſt Being is happy in himſelf. 2. Hence he is acquainted with his own happineſs. 3. Hence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects upon himſelf. 4. Hence he is reflected upon by himſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He ſtands under divers mutual reſpects, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct manners of Being] for his reflecting upon himſelf, and his Being reflected upon by himſelf are mutual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, reflecting hath reſpect to reflected, and reflected hath reſpect to reflecting, and thus they are mutual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And theſe are diſtinct the manners of the Being of the firſt Being, under which he ſtands, hence called Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>the expreſs Image of his perſon,</hi> the word in the Original is Subſiſtence, (the Image of his Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. Theſe manners of Being are only one in reſpect of the Eſſence, and yet are diſtinct from the Eſſence, and one from another,) this is explained in that which follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. How may this be more plainly underſtood?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> God who is the firſt Being knoweth himſelf, and is known of himſelf, and is breathed after by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, all which mutual reſpects belong to the firſt Being, and yet are diſtinct from him, and one from another.</p>
               <p>1. God knows himſelf, otherwiſe he could not be happy in himſelf, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44. 8. 2. Hence he is known of himſelf. 3. Hence he is breathed after by himſelf as the moſt adequate Object of his own perfect underſtanding and will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All which are mutual reſpects, knowing, and being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46814:15"/> known, have a mutual reſpect one to the other, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breathed after by himſelf, hath a mutual reſpect to knowing, and being known by himſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe mutual reſpects belong to the firſt Being, in which we may conſider. 1. The Vnity of the Subſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 2. Their diverſity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Vnity, that whereby the Subſiſtences ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one and the ſame Eſſence, are all God, and one God.</p>
               <p>1. There is but one firſt Being. 2. The Subſiſtences are the firſt being reflecting upon himſelf. 3. Hence theſe are one in Eſſence, one God. Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are Co-Eſſential, having the Eſſence toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and wholly, as when the ſame man is Teacher and Scholar, the Teacher hath the whole man, and the Scholar the whole man, being one and the ſame man, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence they are Co-equal, for they are one God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence the divine Attributes belong to them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually, what doth belong to God as God, doth belong to the Subſiſtences equally, for they are all God and one God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9. 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence they are not God of God, for to be God is the abſolute Being, and this is not relative, and deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, but is one &amp; the ſame in all the perſons, the Son hath his relative being of the Father as he is Son, but not his abſolute Being as God, but thus he is an <hi>Everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the mighty God,</hi> Iſai. 9. 6.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hence the love they have one to another, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to glorifie one another, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of the diverſity of the Subſiſtences, this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in that which followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. How may the Subſiſtences be diſtinguiſht from the Eſſence, and one from another?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:15"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:16"/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46814:16"/> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Subſiſtences may be diſtinguiſht from the Eſſence, as adjunct manners belonging to the ſame Eſſence, and are diſtinguiſht one from another as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, by relative properties, and are not improperly called perſons, for a divine perſon is the Godhead with a relative and individual property, and is either Father, Son, or Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Subſiſtences are diſtinguiſht from the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as adjunct manners belonging to the ſame Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as the ſame hand opening and ſhutting, the beams of the Sun reflecting and reflected, theſe are not the hand nor the Sun, but adjunct manners of the Being of theſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence they differ from the Eſſence only in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, not as divers Eſſences, the ſame hand, the ſame Sun, ſo the ſame God-head reflecting and reflected.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence the Subſiſtences are not divine Attributes, which are one as they are in God, but diverſly appearing to us, but theſe are divers whither we apprehend them ſo or not.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are not inherent qualities in the Eſſence, for there are none ſuch in the Eſſence, as we heard in the deſcription of the Eſſence.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They are manners adhering and belonging to the Eſſence with it and by it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are diſtinguiſht one from another, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates by their relative and individual properties, as teaching and being taught, reflecting and being reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hence followeth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are coexſiſtent, as Relates, for they are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual cauſes, therefore exſiſt together, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 30</p>
               <p n="2">2. Coinexiſtent one in another, for Being and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence is of, and in the cauſe, and they are Relates, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mutual cauſes, &amp; therefore one in another, <hi>Joh</hi> 14. 10</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are coapparant, for knowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the cauſes, and theſe are mutual cauſes, hence he that knows
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46814:17"/> the one, knows the other, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 9.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And yet one is not the other, for Relates are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual cauſes, and differ as cauſe and effect.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence they are not improperly called perſons.</p>
               <p>A perſon is a perfect and individual ſubſtance of a reaſonable nature. 1. A ſubſtance; For meer Accidents or Adjuncts are no perſon, as virtues are not called per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons individual, for mankind is not a perſon, becauſe it's the genus, but individual men are called perſons. 3. Perfect, for the Soul alone is not a perſon, becauſe it's but a part of man, not a perfect man. 4. A reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable nature, creatures without Reaſon are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and by way of eminency it's attributed to men.</p>
               <p>And the God-head with a relative and individual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is a divine perſon, and is either perſons breathing or breathed, <hi>ſpirante</hi> or perſons breathing, as Father and Son, <hi>Spirit,</hi> or breathed, as the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Who is the Father?</head>
               <p>Anſw. The Father is the firſt perſon who begets his Son, God is happy in himſelf. 2. Hence he knows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. 3. Hence he conceivs the Image of himſelf. 4. Hence to conceive and beget, and this may be called active Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, this properly belongeth to the Father, and he is firſt in order 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Who is the Son?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Son is the ſecond divine perſon begotten of the Father. 1. God is happy in himſelf. 2. Hence is known and conceived of himſelf. 3. Hence to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and begotten, and this may be called paſſive gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration, this properly belongs to the Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 18. and he is the ſecond in order.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. Who is the Spirit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Spirit is the third divine perſon proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Father and the Son.</p>
               <p>1. God is happy in himſelf. 2. Hence knoweth and
<pb facs="tcp:46814:17"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:18"/>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:46814:18"/> is known of himſelf. 3. Hence is breathed after by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and this may be called paſſive ſpiration, and is the relative property of the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 14.</p>
               <p>And the Reaſon why active ſpiration doth not conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute a perſon is, becauſe it doth not nextly and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately belong to the divine Eſſence, but to the Father and the Son, for it is God conceiving, and having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Image of himſelf, doth breath after himſelf, and thus active Spiration doth nextly proceed from the Relative properties of the Father, and the Son.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Active ſpiration belongs in common to the Father and the Son, and is no individual property belonging only to one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. What is the Efficiency of God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Efficiency of God is that whereby he worketh all in all things according to the counſel of his will, for his own glory, by his Omnipotency in Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Providence, and which honour of working be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the three perſons, who work the ſame accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their diſtinct manner and order of Subſiſtence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is that whereby he worketh all in all things] for he is the firſt Being, hence the power of working is of him, and hence he is the firſt mover in all other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and worketh all in all, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence appeareth his Omnipotency, if he doth all, then he can do all, hence all powerfulneſs belongeth to him, he can do a work of power.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not that which argueth weakneſs. 1. Hence not that which is contrary to his nature, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 13. and</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence not that which is contrary to the Rule of nature, for the Rule of nature is a beam of his own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. 3. He can do all poſſible things as to raiſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren out of ſtones, which is not to produce an effect without a cauſe, that would be contrary to the Rule of nature and his wiſdome, but he can ſupply the place of the cauſe immediately, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46814:19"/>
               <p> Attribute Omnipotency to him eminently, his power of acting and act is one in him, otherwiſe a change in him, which can not be, but the creature is the Subject of the change not God, the beams of the Sun are in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to warm or ſhine upon this or that thing which they do not in act until that thing comes under the beams of the Sun, and yet no change in the beams of the Sun, but in the thing warmed by the ſame, ſo in reſpect of the power of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. According to the counſel of his will) or his own glory, here appears the decree of God, whereby he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines what ſhall be done.</p>
               <p>1. He can do all things abſolutely poſſible, this is his abſolute power. 2. He will do that only which may ſtand with his wiſdome and good will this is his ordinate power, that he will do only that which is conditionally and reſpectively poſſible, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 11. he could have made more then one woman for one man at firſt, in reſpect of his abſolute power it was poſſible, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 15. but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its inconſiſtency with his wiſdome it was reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively and conditionally impoſſible.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence a decree to determine what ſhall be done and what ſhall not be done, and to this decree belongs that which is Complemental and Eſſential. 1. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental. 1. His truth, his words agree with his mind, <hi>Ier.</hi> 10. 10. 2. His faithfulneſs, he doth what he hath ſaid, and that as he hath ſpoken, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His conſtancy,—his decree can not change, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which is Eſſential to his decree. 1. The fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal cauſe his own glory, for if he intended ultimately any end beſides himſelf, he ſhould deny himſelf, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Efficient cauſes of his decree, his wiſdome and good will. 1. His wiſdome, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 24. 1. He acts well. 2. Hence according to Rule. 3. This Rule is not of the creatures, but of him. 4. This Rule by which
<pb facs="tcp:46814:19"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:20"/>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46814:20"/> he acts is the idea or pattern of well acting. 5. This Idea in God is the firſt cauſe of well acting. 1. It bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth not. 2. Hence its meerly imprinting, and that wiſdome in the creatures is imprinted, and is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion or Image of it. 3. Hence the Rules of Art as in God are eternal, but as in the frame of Creation they are in time, if there had been a man from all Eternity he muſt have been <hi>Animal, Rational,</hi> the definitions of things are eternal Truths, whatever becomes of the things themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other Efficient cauſe of the decree is the will of God, to which we ought to attribute the greateſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, for either he acts freely, or by neceſſity, if by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, then either by outward neceſſity, that which is called the neceſſity of coaction, as forced by an external power, but this can not be, he doth his pleaſure: or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward neceſſity, the neceſſity of nature, as fire burneth, and as all natural cauſes act <hi>ad extremum potentiae,</hi> then he had done all things abſolutely poſſible, but he acted not as a cauſe by neceſſity, nor by nature, but as a cauſe by counſel moſt freely, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 18, 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The goodneſs of his will. 1. He willeth himſelf, as the chiefeſt good. 2. He willeth what is agreeable to himſelf. 3. He ſeeth it to be ſuch, and willeth it as ſuch otherwiſe he might will that which is contrary to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. 4. Hence, becauſe he ſeeth it to be agreeable to himſelf, and beſt, <hi>Conſideratis Conſiderandis,</hi> he willeth it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Efficacy of his will. 1. He willeth the Being and the manner of the Being and acting of a creature, that it be ſuch a creature, and ſo qualified. 2. Hence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e willeth ſome to be natural cauſes, and ſome to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent, and act as cauſes by counſel. 3. Hence he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that man ſhall act freely. 4. Hence he doth not put any neceſſity or conſtraint upon mans will, for then he ſhould act contrary to his own decree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 19. which can not be.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:46814:21"/>
               <p> 1. He willeth what is agreeable to himſelf. 2. Hence his will preſuppoſeth a good, and therefore willeth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But it preſuppoſeth none in the creature, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and worketh it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Independency of his will, it depends not upon any cauſe out of himſelf, only diſtinguiſh between Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praxie and well acting, as it leads to God, and is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to himſelf, and therefore willeth it. And that the Creature may thus act, he willing worketh it<hi>—voluntas decreti,</hi> the will of Gods decree maketh a thing good,<hi>—vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas mandati</hi> the will of his Command enjoyneth the practice of that which is good, hence his commanding will is the Rule of obedience. And God is Omniſcient and Omnipotent, but not Omnivolent, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 35.</p>
               <p>The laſt particular in the deſcription of the Efficiency of God is, that the honour of Efficiency ought to be attributed to all the three divine perſons.]</p>
               <p n="1">1. Efficiency belongeth to God as God, therefore to all the three perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence a cooperation of the perſons. 1. They work the ſame, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 16, 17. 2. They are equal in their working. 3. Hence the cauſal power, a divine perſon putteth forth, is not of another, but of himſelf as God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet a diſtinct manner of working, according to their diſtinct manner and order of Subſiſtence, which order, 1. Is no order of dignity, for they are coequal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No order of time for they are co-Eternal. 3. No order of Exſiſtence and nature, for they are Relates and are coexſiſtent. 4. It is an order of origination. or firſt in numeration, God works by knowing, and being of himſelf, and breathed after by himſelf. Hence,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Father works of himſelf by his Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the origination of things, and eſpecially Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is attributed to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Son worketh from the Father by the Spirit,
<pb facs="tcp:46814:21"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:22"/>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46814:22"/> &amp; thus the diſpenſation of all things is attributed to him; and eſpecially Redemption.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Spirit worketh from the Father, and the Son, by himſelf, and thus the conſummation of things is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to him, and eſpecially the work of application, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 13. 15, 16, 17. the parts of Efficiency followeth, (namely) Creation and Providence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Creation?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Creation is that whereby God made the World out of nothing, very good, in ſix dayes; ſome Creatures were made Immediately out of nothing, as the third Heavens, the Angels, and the firſt matter, and ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately out of nothing, as the Elements, and the Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and amongſt thoſe, laſt of all, man was made.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Creation is that whereby God made the World;] for it was made, or not made; if not made, then no cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of its Being, then no matter nor form, nor end, which cannot be; and either God made it, or it made its ſelf, then it was the cauſe of its own Being, and ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was, which cannot be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Out of nothing] or elſe out of ſome firſt, then out of himſelf, for there was no other firſt Being, then of the ſame Eſſence with him, this cannot be, therefore made out of nothing, or if the World had been Eternall then a numberleſs company of dayes had been before this day, then this day had never been, there is a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of things and times, therefore the World not Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>a parte post.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Very good] goodneſs is a fitneſs for the end. 1. Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, in reſpect of the laſt end to which all ought to ſerve, (namely) the glory of the Creator. 2. Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſubordination of things and ends one to another, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it cometh to the laſt end, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In ſix dayes] <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The parts of the World are Creatures made out of nothing, either Immediately, or mediately. Immediately,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46814:23"/> and were perfect, or imperfect, perfect as the third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and Angels, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Job.</hi> 38. 7.</p>
               <p>Hence theſe were not made out of any preexiſtent prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. 2. Hence their matter and form ſtood together immediately out of nothing, and are conſtant natures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence not ſubject to generation nor corruption, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not acquire nor loſe their form, becauſe made and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by Gods immediate hand, 4. Hence everlaſting. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 20. &amp; 22. 30. The third heavens is that moſt ſtately, and glorious habitation where God is ſeen as it were face to face. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 10.</p>
               <p>The Angels were Spirits made to praiſe God by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miniſtring Spirits. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 7. 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which was made immediately out of nothing, &amp; was imperfect, was the firſt matter; it was a firſt matter, for it was not of the Elements, nor of any pre-exiſtent principle. 2. Made out of nothing, as the third heavens &amp; the Angels, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3. It was imperfect. 1. Without form. 2. Hence no ſpecial nature. 3. Hence no qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes. 4. Hence overſpread with darkneſs, which was not created, but is a meer privation of light. 5. Hence the firſt matter was meerly ſupported by the power of God, otherwiſe it would have fallen into nothing: called Earth in reſpect of its deformity, inferiority and vileneſs.</p>
               <p>Next follows the Creatures, mediately made out of nothing, Elements and Elementaryes.</p>
               <p>1. Elements made out of the firſt matter; but the firſt matter having no form, could give no ſubſtantial form to the Elements. 2. Hence their Forms were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately out of nothing. 3. Hence in reſpect of their ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial natures not ſubject to corruption, but eternal: and though they ſhall change accidentally but not ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially in reſpect of their forms and ſpecial natures; for the heat of the fire ſhall not be extinguiſhed, but remain for ever. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Elements are either the higher or lower,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:24"/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:46814:24"/> The higher, as fire, Air. The Fire is the higheſt and hotteſt Element, and being condenſated it burneth and ſhineth: hence is light, and from light a conſtitution of day and night.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The day is when the light turneth downward, and overſpreads our Hemiſphere.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The night is when the light turneth upward, and overſpreads our Hemiſphere, hence followeth a diviſion of day and night, and this diviſion is by Morning and Evening properly taken.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Morning is the end of darkneſs, and beginning of light, and Evening is the contrary.</p>
               <p>And night and day conſidered together do make up one night-day, called a natural day conſiſting of twenty four hours, the other called a Civil or artificial day.</p>
               <p>And the third Heavens, the Angels, the firſt matter, and the Element of fire from which proceeded Light, was the work of the firſt day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. from the 1. to the 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Air which is a higher Element and moſt moiſt, and as it were the matter of every ſound.</p>
               <p>1. It ſlides into the moſt intimate paſſages, where matter cannot. 2. It is eaſily aſſimilated to the figure of another thing, and therefore is moſt moiſt, called the Firmament, or Expanſe, becauſe it was ſpread as a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and was the work of the ſecond day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 8.</p>
               <p>The lower Elements are water and Earth, the water moſt cold, the Earth moſt dry, and both make one Globe, but the water being next to the Air by order of Creation, and therefore inclineth to ſtand above the Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 6.</p>
               <p>The Elementaries imperfectly mixed, or perfectly mixed. Imperfectly mixed, whoſe parts are not ſo cloſely united as the meteors which ariſe from the fumes of the Elements.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Elementaries perfectly mixed, which have either a body only, or not only a body, but a quickning Spirit,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46814:25"/> a body only in the Minerals, and a body, and a quickning Spirit, and have either a ſingle life, or compound. A ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life, one kind of life only, either ſpringing, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. A ſpringing life as the Plants, and the lower Elements the Meteors, the Minerals and Plants were the work of the third day. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A moving life as the Lights, the greater, or leſſer.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The greater as the Sun and Moon.</item>
                  <item>2. The leſſer, the other Stars the work of the fourth day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 19.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Thoſe which lead a compound life, more lives then one, and either leſs compound or more compound. Leſs compound as Bruits, who are either remote from man, or more nigh to man; remote from man, as Fiſhes and Fowls, the work of the fifth day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 23. or more nigh to man as the Beaſts, made the ſixth day with man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26, 31.</p>
               <p>The moſt compound life as the life of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. How did God make man?</head>
               <p>Anſw. God did make man to conſiſt of a body and a reaſonable, and immortal Soul, according to the Image of God, and gave him dominion over the Creatures, and he was perfectly fitted to pleaſe God.</p>
               <p>In the Creation of man we may conſider his conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and perfection.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His conſtitution or parts, as he conſiſts of body and Soul. 1. His body, which is a part of man made out of the Elements, eſpecially out of the Earth, and fitted with Organs for the Soul.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A part of man with the Soul, hence not his matter only.</item>
                  <item>2. Made of the Elements for it is nouriſh'd by them.</item>
                  <item>3. Eſpecially of the Earth, therefore beareth that Name, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 7.</item>
                  <item>4. Fitted with Organs for the Soul to be its houſe or Tabernacle.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:25"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:26"/>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46814:26"/> 2. The Soul is a quickning Spirit, or ſpiritual ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, immortal, having underſtanding and will, and fitted for union to the body.</p>
               <p>1. A quickning Spirit, or ſpiritual ſubſtance, a Spirit therefore inviſible. 2. A ſubſtance, therefore matter and form.</p>
               <p>1. Matter, elſe it could not ſuffer, for to the matter belongs paſſive principles. 2. Form, otherwiſe deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or boundleſs, for the Form limits the thing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Immortal, for it was made immediately out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and hence returns to him that gave it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Vnderſtanding and will, hence a reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a cauſe by counſel.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fitted for union to the body. 1. The Soul is at firſt united to the body. 2. Hath a fitneſs for it. 3. When ſeperated doth affect this union, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The perfection of man at firſt, a fitneſs to pleaſe God, in which we may conſider the image of God in man, and his dominion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The image of God imprinted on man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
               <p>1. In his underſtanding, he was able to ſee all the Rules which would lead to God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 2. 2. In his will, to chooſe them, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 29. 3. In his affections and body, with all the members thereof fitted to obey the commands of ſanctified Reaſon and will, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Dominion, which was that Royalty of man where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had power to uſe the Creatures for his end, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
               <p>And the woman was joyned with him as a Co-partner with him in this perfection, and his Companion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 22.</p>
               <p>Thus of Creation, in which theſe wonders appear.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God made ſomething out of nothing, his power being infinite.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The act of Creation in reſpect of God Eternal, otherwiſe he ſhould change, which cannot be, but paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46814:27"/> Creation had a beginning, that is, in reſpect of the World made.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Time and place began with the World, having no abſolute being, but relative reſpecting the Creatures hence no time nor place before the World.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Man the <hi>Microcoſmos.</hi> 1. A being, as the Elements. 2. A body as the Minerals. 3 A moving life as ſtars, a ſpringing life as Plants. 4. A ſenſitive life as Beaſts, and 5. A rational life as Angels, and ought to lead a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like life as God, acting his Image in imitation of him, and for him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Providence?</head>
               <p>Anſw. It is that whereby God looketh to his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, either in an ordinary, or extraordinary manner, and therefore preſerveth and governeth them either by his common government, and thus he overruleth all his Creatures, or by his ſpecial government, and thus he ruleth Angels and men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Providence is the Efficiency of God whereby he looketh to his Creatures] watcheth over them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 15, 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is either an ordinary, or extraordinary man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. 1. In an ordinary manner, that is according to the order ſet at firſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 22. 2. Or in an extraordinary manner, not attending to that order, &amp; then the change is not in reſpect of the Rule, but in reſpect of the means, it is not to make an effect without a cauſe, but to ſupply the place of the ordinary cauſe and means by his own power immediately.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Providence is either Conſervation or Government, Conſervation which is that whereby the Being and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the Creatures are continued,] 1. The Creatures have their Being from God. 2. Hence depend upon that ſame cauſal power to continue their Being. 3. The ceſſation or withdrawing of that power will be the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Creature, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 29.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:27"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:28"/>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46814:28"/> 2. Government which is the guiding of the acts of the Creatures to their ends. 1. They were made for ſome end, elſe in vain. 2. They muſt act, otherwiſe how can they attain the end. 3. Some Rule to guide them, elſe not act well. 4. Hence guided &amp; governed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 34, 35.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of cauſes which God governeth cauſes by nature and by Counſel. 1. Natural cauſes which he guides by the Law of nature to their inferior ends. 1. They act by power, or principle ariſing out of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>natura eſt res nata ex principiis,</hi> as water cooleth and fire burneth. 2. Hence determined to one oppoſite, fire of it ſelf burneth only if condenſated. 3. Hence this cauſe acts to the uttermoſt of its power if not hindred by an external power over-ruling. 4. Nature is in all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and God as a God of nature over-ruleth them, therefore this is called a common government, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Cauſes by Counſel, whom God guides in a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal manner by ſpecial Rules to the higheſt end, thus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men. 1. They have Reaſon and liberty of will. 2. Hence are to be guided in a rational manner. 3. This manner is 1. By ſhewing his will. 1. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, and to that annexing a Promiſe. 2. Prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to that annexing a Threatning, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. 8. 2. Fullfilling his will, giving every one his due, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. 19</p>
               <p>And thus the Lord ruleth Angels and Men. 1 Angels, 1. The rule given to them was the moral law, for they were made holy and righteous. 2. The tranſgreſſion of this law was charged upon the fallen Angels as mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and lying: the event of this was,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some of the Angels obeyed and were rewarded</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some diſobeyed and are miſerable. 1. The time of their Fall was before men fell, for they tempted him. 2. Their ſin was Pride, they kept not their ſtation, but aſpired higher, <hi>Jude.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 2. Their puniſhment not in the higheſt degree inflicted untill the laſt day, <hi>Matth.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:46814:29"/> 25. 11. Next of the Government of God reſpecting Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſt. What is the Government of God reſpecting Man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The government of God reſpecting Man at firſt was that whereby God gave man the moral Law and promiſed to reward him with life if he obeyed, and threatned to puniſh him with everlaſting death if he diſobeyed. Concerning the event of which we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Mans <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Anaſtacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The moral Law was given to Man at firſt to be the Rule of Obedience. 1. For he was made holy and righteous. 2. And the tranſgreſſion of this Law was charged upon fallen man: hence the ſame rule with the Angels, only with theſe diſtinctions, 1. Various de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions and applications of the moral Law reſpecting the condition of mans life as he hath a body, as the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, the honouring of Parents, and ſuch like rules were properly belonging to man. 2. As man had ſenſes, and was to be led by ſenſibles to ſpirituals; thus Sacraments were appointed to him. 1. The Tree of life, to aſſure him of life if he obeyed. 2. The tree of knowledge of good and evill to be a ſeal of death if he diſobeyed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Man acted not as every Angel, for himſelf only, but as a publick perſon for himſelf and his poſterity: but more of this in the Apoſtacy of Man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence aroſe a Covenant between God and his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures, Angels and Men: That God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed happineſs upon condition of Obedience, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the contrary upon diſobedience.</p>
               <p>And the event comes to be conſidered reſpecting man in mans Apoſtacy and Anaſtacy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the Apoſtacy of Man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtacy of man is that whereby man did fall from obedience to the Rule of Gods government, in his diſobeying by eating the forbidden fruit, the Devill tempting him to it by abuſing the Serpent and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as inſtruments, and the Man abuſing the liberty of
<pb facs="tcp:46814:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:30"/>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:46814:30"/> his will, the effect of which was guilt and puniſhment upon man and his poſterity.</p>
               <p>In the Apoſtacy of man we may conſider his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and the Propagation of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The tranſgreſſion it ſelf in eating the forbidden fruit. 1. He had liberty to eat any other. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 16. 2. It was againſt an expreſs command. 3. An abuſe of the Sacrament; and thus a contempt of the whole Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17.</p>
               <p>And we may conſider the cauſes of his ſin, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it. The cauſes, a blameable, and blameleſs, the blameable, adjuvant and principal, the adjuvant or help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſes, the Devil abuſing the Serpent and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 1 The Devil tempted. 1. Pretending a good. 2. Concealed, yea, denyed the evil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Abuſed the Serpent which had a natural ſubtlety which Satan abuſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 3. Abuſed the woman, who being next to man might be moſt likely to perſwade man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The principal, blameable cauſe was mans abuſing the liberty of his will, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 29.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Man as a Creature was mutable, immutability is a property of the Creator, and mutability is inſeperable from the Creature, that is a poſſibility to change, and this belonging to a Creature as a Creature, and not as a ſinful Creature, is no ſinful defect.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As man was a cauſe by counſel he had reaſon and liberty of will, and that liberty of indifferency, could chuſe and refuſe, had no neceſſity upon his will.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Adam had the image of God, ſo he was able to have obeyed if he would. 1. He had perfection. 2. This was not taken away before his fall; for then he had not been perfect before his fall.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence his firſt ſin did not ariſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. From any ſinfull principle in him, for 1. He was perfect and had no ſuch principle. 2. The eating of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46814:31"/> forbidden fruit was his firſt ſin, but if it had aroſe from any ſinful principle in him, that diſpoſition to ſin had been his firſt ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence firſt ſin was not error in underſtanding, for either he had not ability to diſcern, or he did not uſe it. Not the firſt, for he had perfection of intellectual vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; if the ſecond, a neglect to uſe his ability, this was not error in underſtanding, but rather of his will.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence his firſt ſin was a conſent of his will to Satans Temptation. 1. Satan preſents a good. 2. Tempts to unlawful means, and man inordinately chuſeth the one, and is overcome by the other,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence man put himſelf under the power of his mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability, and thus abuſeth the liberty of his will, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. 29. that a glaſs is breakable is not a defect to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, but that man who was mutable would t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y whether by an unlawful means he could not attain a good, and thus put himſelf under the power of mutabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and thus this glaſs is broken and undone,</p>
               <p n="2">2. The blameleſs cauſe was the Law of God. 1. The Law forbids ſin. 2. Man oppoſeth it. 3. The Law muſt yield, or man muſt be broken. 4. The Law cannot yield, or give place, but is like a Rock againſt which a Ship runneth, and breaks it ſelf in pieces, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 15.</p>
               <p>The Effect of this was, firſt guilt, <hi>2dly,</hi> puniſhment.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Guilt, whereby a tranſgreſſor is bound to ſuffer puniſhment, or is lyable to it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 19.</item>
                  <item>2. Puniſhment, namely the evil inflicted upon a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for his tranſgreſſion, which is death it ſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the puniſhment of ſin?</head>
               <p>Anſw. The puniſhment of ſin is death, which is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a happy life, and being ſubject to the contrary miſery, both the firſt death, the body deprived of the comforts of this life, and at laſt ſevered from the Soul, and the ſecond death which is the death of the Soul.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Death is the puniſhment of ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:31"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:32"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:46814:32"/> 2. It is a privation of a happy life] not meerly a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of life, for then Being ſhould ceaſe, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of miſery be taken away, and ſo the puniſhment ended, but it is a privation of a happy or comfortable life, hence the parts of death are, 1. A privation of the good, and 2. The ſenſe of the contrary miſery. 3. The kinds of death, the firſt death, the ſecond death. The firſt death, a corporeal death, the beginning of which is in a privation of the comforts of this life in ſome degree, &amp; the contrary miſeries, poverty, ſhame, ſickneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10. 2. The perfection of this is when Soul &amp; body are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated, &amp; the body returns to the Elements, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12. 7.</p>
               <p>The ſecond death, which is the death of the Soul.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the death of the Soul?</head>
               <p>Anſw. The death of the Soul is firſt a privation of that which is Eſſential to ſpiritual life, as the principle of life, the Image of God, and the contrary evil poſſeſſing (namely) a principle of Enmity in mans nature againſt God, and a privation of the acts of life, and a ſwerving of mans actions from God, the firſt may be called original ſin, and the other actual ſin.</p>
               <p>In the death of the Soul we may conſider it as it is a privation of that which is Eſſential to ſpiritual life. 2. Of that which belongs to its well Being.</p>
               <p>1. Of that which is Eſſential, as firſt, a privation of a principle of life, and ſo of the Image of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 18. man oppoſing the Law, defaced the Image of God, and ſpoyled himſelf. 2. Hence was ſubjected to a principle of Enmity againſt God, and thus a ſwerving of his whole nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5. &amp; thus ſin taketh occaſion by the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A privation of acts of life, and the contrary to this a ſwerving of the actions from the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe is called Original ſin, as it is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ſpring of the other, and the latter is called
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46814:33"/> actual ſin, as it is the acting of vicious principles which are in mans nature, <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 18, 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the death of the ſoul in the ſecond place?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Death of the Soul in the ſecond place is a privation of the favour of God, and being poſſeſſed with fear and ſhame: a privation of the confirming preſence of God, and being ſubject to the power of Satan: and the conſummation of this death ſhall be when the Soul immediately after its departure out of the body ſhall be caſt into hell, and both ſoul and body after the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>In the former we hear of a privation of that which is eſſential to a ſpiritual life, next of that which belongs to the well being and compleating of that life.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A privation of the favour of God. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 43, 44. And the contrary to this, poſſeſſed with fear and ſhame. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57. <hi>ult. Gen.</hi> 3. 7, 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A privation of the confirming preſence of God: Man ſhould have been eſtabliſhed in the way of life if he had obeyed; but he diſobeying is deprived of this: and the contrary to this is a being ſubject to the power of Satan the tempter. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Eph</hi> 2. 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The perfection of this death. 1. The Soul imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after its departure out of the body ſhall be caſt into hell. 2. The Soul and Body after the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment together caſt into hell fire: <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 50. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 14 15. <hi>Math.</hi> 16. 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the propagation of Adams ſin unto his Poſterity?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Adams Tranſgreſſion is extended to all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; for all mankind was in him as the common root, and he acted as a publick perſon, and therefore his ſin is imputed to all his poſterity, and he hath really commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated the ſame ſinfull nature, that we are inclined to act as he did.</p>
               <p>We may conſider the union of Adams poſterity to him, and their communion with him.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:33"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:34"/>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:46814:34"/> 1. The union, Natural, Moral. 1. Natural: all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind was in him, as he was the common root of all mankind. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 26. Hence what he acted all Mankind did act. 2. The moral union: He acted as a publick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if he had obeyed, all his poſterity had been happy; he diſobeying all become miſerable. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Communion with him, by imputation, and real communication. 1. Imputation: his ſin is reckoned to his poſterity as if they had done it, hence in reſpect of the merit of it accounted theirs, hence guilt and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A real communication of the ſame ſinful nature Original ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3.] Thus it is natural, ſuch as the Root ſuch are the Branches,] 2. Sin is conveyed either from God, or from the Parents, not from God, for he cannot be the author of ſin, hence the Soul as it comes out of his hand is not poſitively holy, for then there might be a falling from grace, ſeeing many Children appear to be wicked afterwards, and yet the Soul as it comes out of his hand is not poſitively vicious, for he cannot be the author of ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence ſin comes to the Child nextly from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and that firſt, is either immediately, but not ſo, for the Soul of a Child is not immediately united to the Parents, therefore can have no ſuch communion with them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or mediately, and that is either by the Body or the Spirits which unite Soul and body, not from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy nextly, for that is united to the Soul by the Spirits, hence it is by the deordination of thoſe Spirits which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Soul and body, and theſe are conveyed from the Parents, and not under the power of diſtemper and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and Communion is by union, and union is by the uniting means.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What Attributes ſhine forth in the Apoſtacy of man?</head>
               <p>Anſw. The holineſs and Juſtice, and yet the mercy of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46814:35"/> God in gentleneſs and bounty to fallen man do ſhine forth, in, or by occaſion of mans Apoſtacy.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The holineſs of God which is that whereby he cannot approve of any, but thoſe who do agree with him, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance him as he is moſt glorious, hence he diſtaſted man, and abhorred man, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Juſtice inclined to give every one his due. 1. Remunerative, in rewarding him who doth well, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 4. 2. Vindictive, in puniſhing him who doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 9. and the degrees of this. 1. The Sentence called Judgement. 2. The Execution of it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8. 11. the degrees of this, firſt, if more mild called anger, if more ſharp called wrath and fury, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 23.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His mercy inclined to ſuccour the undeſerving, hence firſt, gentleneſs inclined to ſpare a ſinner in bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, called patience, if long, his long ſufferance, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11. 36. 15, 16. 2. His bounty inclined to afford ſupplies to the undeſerving, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 4. Man ſuffers Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure for ſin, but this man through his weakneſs can not bear, and therefore breaks under it, and cannot ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, and therefore it is juſt he ſhould alwayes ſuffer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the Anaſtacy of Man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Anaſtacy of man is that whereby the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God recovereth ſome ſinners out of a ſtate of ſin &amp; death, into a ſtate of grace and life by the redemption of the Son of God, whoſe work it is to reconcile God and man as he is Prieſt, and man to God as he is a Prophet and King, and by his Spirit ſent to apply this Redemption.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Anaſtacy of man is his recovery out of a ſtate of ſin and death, into a ſtate of grace and life,] <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This proceeds from the mercy of God, whereby he is inclined to ſuccour the miſerable, and the undeſerving, and therefore this is done for his own Names ſake, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43. 25.</p>
               <p>The parts of this are, Redemption, Application. 1. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which is a payment of a juſt price to divine
<pb facs="tcp:46814:35"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:36"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:46814:36"/> Juſtice, and thereby ſatisfaction. 1. God governs man as he is a reaſonable creature. 2. Hence according to Juſtice. 3. Hence if man had obeyed he ſhould have been rewarded with life, but he having diſobeyed, he cannot live without juſt ſatisfaction made, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 17.</p>
               <p>Concerning Redemption we may conſider the perſon and his work. 1. The perſon who is the Redeemer, the Son of God. 1. God and man at variance, the Father in ſpecial, the perſon offended, man by his ſin having made a breach upon the work of Creation, in which work the Fathers manner of working did ſhine forth, as we heard in the Efficiency of God, hence it was not meet for him to mediate. 2. This work is propounded to the Son of God, and he accepts it, and his manner of working doth eſpecially ſhine forth in this, who is the ſecond divine perſon, and this is the ſecond great work, and he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the Father by the Spirit, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 6. <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His firſt work, <hi>to reconcile God to man,</hi> as a Prieſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 17. 2. To reconcile man to God, firſt, as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet making known the way of life, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 18. 2. As a King, diſpenſing life with a Kingly Authority, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 1, 2, 3. And by his Spirit ſent to apply this Redemption, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 8, 9, 10, 11. but of this afterwards. The firſt being the Sufficiency, the ſecond the Efficiency of mans Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy or recovery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What in the first place ought to be conſidered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this work?</head>
               <p>Anſw. We ought in the firſt place to conſider the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt to be a Redeemer, for his two natures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſonally united, and yet remain the ſame in Eſſence and Eſſential properties, and he was anointed, that is, called and furniſhed to this great work of Redemption.</p>
               <p>To the performing of the work of a Redeemer, we may conſider, firſt, a fitneſs of Chriſt to redeem. 2. The parts of Redemption. Firſt, of his fitneſs to redeem ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in his Incarnation and Vnction. Firſt, his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46814:37"/> the Son of God was made man in all things ſin on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted, and the manner of his Subſiſtence. 1. <hi>He was like to us,</hi> Phil. 2. 7. 2. <hi>in all things,</hi> Heb. 2. 17. 3. <hi>except ſin,</hi> he was without ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 15. and the manner of the Subſiſtence of his humane nature, for that ſubſiſts in his divine perſon, in which we may conſider the union of his natures, and their Communion. 1. Their union, which is that whereby the Son of God aſſumed a humane nature, to ſubſiſt inſeperably in his own perſon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The perſon aſſuming, was the Son of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4. hence it was God aſſumed a humane nature, and yet not as God, for then all the three perſons had aſſumed. 2. But the Son of God aſſumed mediately by his perſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which is aſſumed is a humane nature, Soul and body, hence 1. a twofold underſtanding, <hi>Mark</hi> 13. 32. 2. A twofold will, divine and humane, accompanied with a natural deſire of his ſafety, <hi>Math.</hi> 26. 39. 3. And a twofold preſence, Omnipreſent as God, but not ſo as man</p>
               <p n="3">3. The aſſumption it ſelf, his humane nature did not ſubſiſt by its ſelf, for then it had been a perſon, and then two perſons mediating, but there is but one Mediator, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His humane nature ſubſiſted in his perſon. 1. It was ſuſtained by it from the beginning of its Being, and thus was related to the divine nature as an Effect, or an Adjunct. 2. It was filled with the divine nature, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 9. and thus the divine nature had a twofold reſpect of Subſiſtence, one in the Godhead as he was the ſecond perſon, this was from Eternity; another in the humane nature in time, and yet but one Subſiſtence, for this works no change in the divine nature, only a relation is added to it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Subſiſteth in it inſeperably,] for if this union had been broken, then no Mediator, not God-man in one perſon, hence when Soul and body were ſevered, yet the divine nature preſerved its union to both of them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 31.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:37"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:38"/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:46814:38"/> 4. Hence aſſuming was no act of Chriſts Humiliation for, 1. It was an act of his divine perſon, and that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer. 2. If it were an act of Humiliation, it ſhould be laid aſide in the ſtate of his Exaltation, then the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts natures ſhould ceaſe in heaven, but this cannot be.</p>
               <p>Thus of the union. Next of the Communion of Chriſts natures: only we muſt remember, 1. Their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. 2. But no Confuſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Communion, which is perſonal, for ſuch is their union.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hence they co-operate to the ſame effect, if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature doth effect that to which the humane nature doth not concur, then no work of God-man, if the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature did that in which the divine did not concur, then no act of the Perſon; hence they co-operate to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Its according to their properties and diſtinct man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working: when the humane nature was the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the divine nature was the Altar, which ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Sacrifice: and as he was God and man he was the Prieſt, and when his body was raiſed out of the grave this divine nature acted in that work by virtue of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the humane nature.</p>
               <p>Hence what is proper to the Perſon is attributed to the humane nature by reaſon of its relation, as to be in the beginning; and what belongs to one nature is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to another, as God manifeſted in the fleſh. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hence the humane nature is to be worſhipped, not in reſpect of it ſelf, but as united to the divine nature. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
               <p>And yet the diſtinction of his natures remain, that is they remain the ſame in eſſence and eſſential properties.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In eſſence, his divine nature cannot be a humane nature, that cannot change; his humane nature cannot be a divine nature, for finite cannot become infinite.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:46814:39"/> 2. Diſtinct in their eſſential properties, that although they doe make uſe of one anothers propertyes, yet the eſſence remaining diſtinct, their eſſential properties are diſtinct; a divine and an humane underſtanding, will and preſence, as we ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Thus of the Incarnation, next of Chriſts Vnction, Call, Furniture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Call, his Father called him, that is 1. Choſe him to this work, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42. 1, 2. 2. Gave him a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 17. 3. Promiſed to proſper and reward him. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 10. 11. And Chriſt accepted of this work, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 6, 7. Hence a Covenant between the Father and the Son, and thus in this reſpect our Mediator was eternal. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Furniture. 1. A fullneſs of grace, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 16. beyond meaſure, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 39. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 1, 2.</p>
               <p>Hence all the three Perſons have their hand in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. 1. In making the humane nature. 2. In uniting the humane nature to the divine nature; for theſe belong to the efficiency of God as he is God. 3. But the ſecond Perſon only aſſumes it, he alone is the term of that Relation, their act terminates only on and in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why muſt Chriſt be God and Man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Chriſt muſt be man that he might ſuffer for man and teach man familiarly, and be of the ſame kind with his body; and he was God, that he might enable his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature to ſuffer, and that he might be a moſt able Prophet, and be able to ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly his body, and rule as King.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He was man that he might ſuffer for man; for man had ſinned, and man muſt ſuffer: and he was God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able his humane nature to ſuffer. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2 He was man that he might teach man familiarly after the manner of man, and he was God that he might be an able Prophet, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 16.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:39"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:40"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:46814:40"/> 3. He was man that he might be of the ſame kind with his body, the head and the body muſt be of the ſame kind, and yet he muſt be God, that he might be able to ſupply his body, and to rule as King, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 21, 22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 17, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are the parts of Redemption?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The parts of Redemption are Chriſts humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his Exaltion, 1. His humiliation, whereby he ſatisfied for offences, and merited life, humbling himſelf in his life, and eſpecially in his death.</p>
               <p>The parts of Redemption are humiliation and Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1. Chriſts humiliation whereby he ſatisfied for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. 1. Man had ſinned. 2. Hence ought to ſuffer puniſhment. 3. Chriſt as a Surety beareth the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 4. He ſatisfied for offences by his paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Merited life. 1. If man had obeyed he ſhould have been rewarded with life. 2. Hence no reward without doing well. 3. Chriſt doth perform this. 4. Hence Chriſt merited by his active obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 19. paſſive obedience did only ſatisfie for the breach and wrong, but it was his active obedience which did merit the reward, namely life and happineſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Humbling himſelf in his life, and eſpecially in his death, the conſideration of theſe followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What was the Humiliation of Chriſt in his life?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſts humiliation in his life was firſt in reſpect of his private life, his body was born of the Seed of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and both Soul and body having been made and ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt, in his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he was Circumciſed, and offered, and fled into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and become ſubject to his Mother, and afterwards la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with his hands, until he came to his publick life.</p>
               <p>The humiliation of Chriſt in his life, private and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick life. 1. Private life, his admiſſion into the World, commoration in it. 1. His admiſſion, in which his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Nativity. 1. His Conception, his body was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46814:41"/> born of the Seed of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> both Soul and body made and ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt. 1. His body was of the Seed of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> as the paſſive principle, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 35. the holy thing born of her. 2. Thus he was of the Seed of the woman according to the promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. 3. <hi>Mary</hi> was of the Seed of <hi>David,</hi> hence Chriſt was king of the Jews by birth, being of the Seed of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Math. 2. 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Both Soul and body were made and ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt as the active principle, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 35. 1. His Soul made immediately out of nothing, created by infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and infuſed by creating, as the Soul of man is. 2. His body formed by the holy Ghoſt, hence though of the Seed of the woman, yet not of the Seed of man. 2. Hence the courſe of Original ſin was ſtopt, and he was called that holy thing, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 35. 2. Sanctified by the holy Ghoſt] Soul and body united and raiſed to the higheſt perfection. 1. In reſpect of habitual perfection there could be no addition. 2. In reſpect of actual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection there might be, and was a growth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 52. thus in reſpect of his humane nature he was a Son with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Father, in reſpect of his divine nature, a Son with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Mother, tipified by <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> Heb. 7. 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Nativity of Chriſt, he was born of <hi>Mary,</hi> the wife of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> before they came together, after ſhe had gone a full time, <hi>Math.</hi> 1. 25.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Commoration in the World. 1. His private and publick life, and 1. His private life, 1. In his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy circumciſed and offered, and thus performed the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 21, 22. 2. Flight into <hi>Egypt,</hi> he was born to miſery, and yet was to deliver his people out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Math 1. 21. 3. His ſubjection to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; thus fulfilled the Moral Law, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 51. his diſpute with the Doctors when he was about twelve years of Age, to ſhew that he needed not to be taught of man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 42, 46, 47. and his labouring with his hands, and
<pb facs="tcp:46814:41"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:42"/>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:46814:42"/> thus did bear the curſe of our labours. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 3. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What was the Humiliation of Chriſt in his publick life.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt's Humiliation in his publick life was that whereby he entred into his publick life, with bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and temptation, and his courſe in, it was a going about doing good in poverty and much labour, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and working of miracles: &amp; towards the concluſion, prepared himſelf and his Diſciples for his death.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt entred into his publick life with Baptiſm &amp; Temptation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By Baptiſme, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 15. ſhewing himſelf to be the band of both the Covenants, and that the Covenant of works and the covenant of grace were performed in and by him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Temptation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>the beginning of that Chap.</hi> ſhewing he was come upon his trial, and ſhould over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and be able to ſuccor the tempted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His courſe in his publick life in going about doing good. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 38. 1. in poverty. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 9. 2. In much labour, 1. In preaching. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 18. 2. Working Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of all ſorts, which was proper to Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 5, 6</p>
               <p n="3">3. Towards the concluſion prepared himſelf and his Diſciples for his death, by his practice, and his ſpeech.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His practice, 1. His Example in giving ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent pattern of humility and love in waſhing his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples feet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>to the</hi> 18. 2. More eſpecially in his Tranſfiguration, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. 2. And his Celebration of the Paſſover, and aboliſhing of that, thereby ſhewing he was the lamb to be offered up, and appointing his Supper in the place of it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 17. 26.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By his ſpeech, 1. To God in prayer, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 27. his moſt ſolemn prayer in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 2. His ſpeech to his diſciples in the 14, 15, 16. <hi>Chapters of</hi> John.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What was the Death of Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt's death was the extream puniſhment he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46814:43"/> ſuffered, firſt before his Crucifixion eſpecially in his ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Garden, and his being arreſted by a band of men with <hi>Judas,</hi> &amp; being arraigned, he ſuffered extream igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny by deriſion and whipping, and the ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; but principally his ſuffering the Crucifixion it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Chriſts death was the extream puniſhment he ſuffered before his Crucifixion, eſpecially in his Crucifixion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Before his Crucifixion; 1. Before his arraignment, 1. His Soul trouble, eſpecially his Agony in the garden <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 44. 2. His being arreſted by a band of men with <hi>Judas, ver.</hi> 47, <hi>and</hi> 52.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His being arraigned before civil and eccleſiaſtical Tribunal. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 54. Thus Juſtice purſued our Surety. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53. 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Vpon his arraignment followed, 1. His Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream ignominy by deriſion and ſcourging. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 67. A Sentence of condemnation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 27. He was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached as a Deceiver, a falſe Prophet, a Blaſphemer, and many other horrible crimes, for he ſuffered for all ſorts of ſins, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What was Chriſts Crucifixion?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſts Crucifixion was that whereby he was lifted up and hanged upon a croſs, and ſo being made a curſe, languiſhed to death, and ſuffering both a bodily and ſpiritual death, gave up the Ghoſt, and his body con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the grave three dayes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. His Crucifixion is that whereby he was lifted up and hanged upon the croſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27. 35.</item>
                  <item>2. And thus was made a curſe and languiſhed to death. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. hence the death he ſuffered was,</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. A curſed death, the hanging upon the croſs being a <hi>Symbolum</hi> or ſign of the curſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A moſt ſhamefull death, hanged up between the heaven and the earth, as if the heaven at preſent rejected him, and as if the earth would not bear him.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:44"/>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:46814:44"/> 3. A moſt tormenting death in pain and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, eſpecially conſidering the perfection of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and ſenſes, and conſequently the pam he felt was the greater, being perfectly ſenſible of pain.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Suffering both a bodily and a ſpiritual death. 1 A ſpiritual death, wholly deprived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſenſe of the ſweetneſs of the love of the Father, and poſſeſſed with the ſenſe of the contrary bitterneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 46. 2. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily death, He gave up the Ghoſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 50.</p>
               <p>1. He was a Surety for ſinners. 2. Hence he was to ſuffer death. 3. Hence muſt ſhed his heart blood. 4. Hence wholly deprived of the life of joy and comfort in Soul and body. 5. But yet not left to ſin, for that befals man becauſe he is weak and breaks under the puniſhment of ſin, but Chriſt was able to endure the worſt and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the puniſhment.</p>
               <p>The conſequence of his death, his body continued in the grave three dayes; <hi>Luk</hi> 24. 7.</p>
               <p>1. He had endured the puniſhment reſpecting ſenſe, when he ſaid it is finiſhed. 2. Yet continued in the ſtate of death. 1. His body buryed. 2. His Soul ſeperated from it, though not ſuffering pain. 3. The union of his Soul, and likewiſe of his body continued unto his divine perſon, that although they were ſevered one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet they remain united to his divine perſon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 31.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of Redemption (namely) Chriſts Exaltation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Chriſts Exaltation?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Exaltation of Chriſt is his Tryumph over his and our Enemies; the degrees of which are his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead, his aſcenſion into Heaven, his ſeſſion at the right hand of the Father, and at the end of the World, his return in glory to be the Judge of the World.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Exaltation, that is his Tryumph over his and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46814:45"/> our Enemies, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 35, 36. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 8, 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The degrees of which Exaltation. 1. Before the end of the World. 2. At the end of the world. 1. Before the end of the world. 1. His Reſurrection, his body raiſed, Soul and body reunited, and this done by his God-head, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 4. and ſeen by his Diſciples forty dayes, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Aſcenſion. 1. His humane nature aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the higheſt Heavens by the power of his God-head, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 10, 11. his Diſciples being witneſſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 10, 11</p>
               <p n="3">3. His ſeſſion at the right hand of his Father, which holds forth 1. His entertainment by his Father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 1. having accepted him, and put all things under him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21, 22, 27. 2. He well ſatisfied with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 11. 3. Hence his Interceſſion, he preſents his merits, claimeth the performance of what was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him, reſpecting his glory and the good of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 24, 25.</p>
               <p n="2">2. At the end of the World, his return in glory to be the Judge of the World, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 16, 17.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Chriſts humiliation the glory of Chriſts divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was hidden, but not diminiſhed, in his Exaltation it is manifeſted, but not augmented.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His humane nature was really abaſed, and really exalted, enjoying the actings of the glory of his divine nature according to its manner and meaſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the day of Judgement is come and finiſht, he will deliver up his Kingdome to his Father, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, and ſo to continue for ever, but not ſo as to put an end to his Head-ſhip, and Mediator-ſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, 28.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The degrees of his Exaltation are according to the degrees of his humiliation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt dyed, and he roſe again.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He deſcended into Hell, and he aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His body lay in the grave three dayes, that is, a part of all the three dayes, and he ſits now at the right
<pb facs="tcp:46814:45"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:46"/>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:46814:46"/> hand of his Father, and ſhall come in great glory to judge the World.</p>
               <q>Next of Application.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Application of Chriſts Redemption?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Application of Chriſts Redemption is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of mans recovery, whereby that which Chriſt hath done as a Mediator is applyed to thoſe whom the Father hath elected, &amp; made theirs effectually by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and giveth common gifts to others, in which let us conſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What is applyed] that which Chriſt hath done as a Mediator. 1. That which he purchaſed by his humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 2. And poſſeſſeth in his Exaltation for his, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To whom is this Application of Redemption made, it is applyed to thoſe whom the Father hath elected. 1. The Father hath intended the ſalvation of a certain number of mankind, theſe are his by Election. 2. Thoſe and thoſe only he hath given to his Son, theſe are Chriſts by donation from his Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 37. 3. Theſe Chriſt only intends to ſave, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 9, 10. 4. Hence no univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Redemption, for either theſe elected he intends only to redeem, or others beſides them, then it ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain to God who ſhall be ſaved, which cannot be, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 1. and if it depends meerly upon the liberty of mans will, it ſhould be uncertain whether any ſhall be ſaved, yea, it would be certain then none could be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for none by nature is ſincerely willing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 2. 3. but the Lords foundation remaineth ſure, he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his own, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet it may be granted, that which Chriſt hath done. 1. Is of univerſal value] hath worth enough in it for the ſalvation of all. 2. It is offered to all. 3. Man not knowing who are excluded out of, or included in Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ought to hope charitably, hence it followeth.</p>
               <p>Herein appears Predeſtination, (namely) the Decree
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46814:47"/> of God concerning the manifeſtation of his glory in the everlaſting ſtate of man, electing ſome, and reprobating others. 1. Election. 1. He intends the glory of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. 2. He chuſeth ſome to be Veſſels of his mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 23. 3. Hence willeth the means. 1. permits their fall. 2. Willeth their recovery by Redemption, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Reprobation. 1. The Lord intends the glory of his Juſtice. 1. Some appointed for that end, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 22. 2. Permitted them to ſin, and to continue hardened in ſin to their deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Application it ſelf, that which Chriſt hath done is made theirs effectually, for either it is made theirs by effectual Application to them, or it may be theirs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is applyed to them, but that cannot be, for before Redemption be applyed to them, they are Children of wrath as others, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>the wrath of God abideth on them,</hi> Joh. 3. 36. they cannot be ſaved and damned at the ſame time, hence Election works no change in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, doth not change his ſtate before effectual Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By whom is this Application made, it is by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſent from the Father and the Son.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it requireth an almighty power, a divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo it is the work of all the three perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As they co-operate according to their manner of Subſiſtence and order of working, it is of the Father firſtly by his Son and Spirit. 2. It is of the Son as he works from the Father by the Spirit. 3. It is of the Spirit as he worketh from the Father and the Son.</p>
               <p>And hence ſalvation is of the Father intentionally in Election. 2. Of the Son virtually, as he hath purchaſed ſalvation. 3. Of the Spirit effectually, as he is ſent to apply this, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 9, 10. and giveth common gifts to others for the ſake of his Elect, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 8, 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are the parts of Application and the manner of applying thoſe parts?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:47"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:48"/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:46814:48"/> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The parts of Application are union to Chriſt, that is Oneneſs in relation to Chriſt, and Communion with Chriſt, that is having in common with Chriſt, the bleſſings he hath purchaſed, and the manner of Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe is either internal, and myſtical, this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to true believers, or external and viſible, and this Hipocrites have in common with true believers.</p>
               <p>Application may be conſidered either in the parts of it, or adjunct manners. 1. The parts of it, that is ſuch parts as doe conſtitute it, and of which it doth conſiſt, union to Chriſt, Communion with Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Vnion to Chriſt] that is an Oneneſs in relation to Chriſt, whereby they are Chriſts, and Chriſt is theirs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not an Eſſential Oneneſs, to be one in Eſſence with Chriſt, this is proper to the three perſons thus to be one.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not a perſonal Oneneſs, this is proper to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature of Chriſt to be one with his divine nature to ſubſiſt inſeperably in the ſame perſon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such a relative oneneſs, ſo that the Lord Chriſt owneth the Soul, and the Soul owneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and as true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one with Chriſt in a ſpiritual ſenſe, as the bridegroom and the bride. <hi>Cant.</hi> 6. 3. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 17, 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Communion with Chriſt, whereby we have in common with Chriſt the bleſſings he hath purchaſed. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3. As a woman by mariage hath the benefits of a mariage relation in common with her husband.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This union to, and communion with Chriſt may be conſidered in reſpect of the manners of it, in which we have the diſtribution of the ſubject from its adjuncts, and thoſe conſidered, as proper or common,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Proper to true Believers, and ariſeth out of the ſpecial nature of application, is that internal and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſincere union to, and communion with Chriſt, which although it may be ſeen by him who hath it, and may be ſeen by others as to the Judgement of Charity, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46814:49"/> be ſeen by others as to the Judgement of verity and infallibility, and therefore may be called inward and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 28. and this is proper to true believers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or that which is common (namely) an external and viſible union to, and Communion with Chriſt. 1. In words they ſpeak as ſuch. 2. In works outwardly they practice as ſuch, who have union to Chriſt and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him. 3. And therefore to the Judgement of rational Charity appear to be ſuch. 4. And have really an external and viſible union to Chriſt, as Chriſt is the head of his viſible Church. 5. But this is that which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites have in common with true believers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 28.</p>
               <p>Let us begin with that which is internal and myſtical union to Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is that internal and mystical union to Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Internal and myſtical union to Chriſt is that whereby the Spirit having wrought Faith in the heart cauſeth the ſoul to come to Chriſt for life, and is joyned to Chriſt as its ſpiritual head.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That whereby the ſpirit having wrought faith in the heart, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 17.</item>
                  <item>2. Cauſeth the ſoul to come to Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 4. for life. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 40.</item>
                  <item>3. And is joyned to Chriſt as its ſpiritual head. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 22. and this is internal and myſtical, none knows but he that hath it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 17.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> In what manner doth the Spirit work Faith?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Spirit doth work Faith by an unreſiſtible power, he prepareth the heart by making it contrite and humble, and then infuſeth Faith.</p>
               <p>Concerning the working of Faith conſider who work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, and how.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Who worketh it] It is wrought by the unreſiſtible power of the Spirit. 1. Thoſe who are dead cannot of themſelves move, ſo are all by nature, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. 2. By
<pb facs="tcp:46814:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:50"/>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:46814:50"/> nature a meer reſiſtance againſt the Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 51. 3. Hence the Soul at firſt is paſſive in this work, moves as moved. 4. The power at firſt put forth by the Spirit is exceeding great, more then at Creation, for then as there was nothing, ſo there was no reſiſtance, but here is not a meer emptineſs and nothingneſs, but worſe, a Spirit of reſiſtance againſt the work of Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How he worketh it by preparation and infuſion. 1. Preparation before the infuſion of Faith. 1. So long as there is a reſiſting, there can be no receiving, conſent and diſſent cannot be in the ſame Subject, in the ſame part, reſpect and time. 2. But to reſiſt and not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is natural, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 7. 3. Hence the power of reſiſtance muſt be taken away before an infuſion of Faith, a turning from ſin and ſelf, before there can be a turning unto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This preparation is in contrition and humiliation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Contrition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Contrition?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Contrition is that whereby a ſinner being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the evil of ſin, and feeling the bitterneſs of it, is broken under the burthen of it, and broken off from the ſame with a hatred, ſorrow, abomination, and fear of ſin as the greateſt evil.</p>
               <p>Contrition conſiſts of conviction and compunction.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Conviction, whereby a ſinner is convicted of the evil of ſin. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 8. <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 19.</item>
                  <item>2. Compunction, a pricking of the heart, letting in a ſenſe of the bitterneſs of ſin into the heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 37. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 10.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The effect of this brokenneſs of heart, 1. Vnder the burden of ſin as too heavy to bear. 2. And off from ſin as a moſt deteſtable ſoe; and this appears.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 In reſpect of ſins paſt and preſent, 1. Hatred. 2. Sorrow. 3. Abomination. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11.</item>
                  <item>2 In reſpect of the future, a fear. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 17.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:46814:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt,</hi> What is Humiliation?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Humiliation is that whereby a ſinner deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of life in himſelf, and of any ability of himſelf to go to Chriſt, is content to be at the diſpoſe of God, and is brought down to the foot of God, hence is poor in ſpirit and is cut off from ſelf confidence and ſelf-ſoveraignty.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Humiliation is that whereby a ſinner deſpaireth of life in himſelf] for he ſees himſelf to be naked and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17, 18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And of any ability in himſelf to goe to Chriſt] that he is blind, maimed and halt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence is content to be at the foot of God, at the Lords diſpoſe] <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. 2. hence poor in ſpirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 3. And thus is cut from ſelf-confidence, and ſelf-ſeveraignty.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From ſelf-confidence] he feels its in vain for him to lean upon any thing that he hath or can doe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From ſelf-ſoveraignty, for he is weary of the yoke of ſin, and he cannot rule himſelf, he is weary of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and heavy laden. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7 20. <hi>Mat</hi> 11. 28, 29.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the infuſion of Faith?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The infuſion of Faith is the pouring into the heart a ſpirit of faith whereby the ſoul is affected toward Chriſt as a giver of life, and by means of the covenant of grace cometh to Chriſt for life, and is joyned to him as its head.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This infuſion of Faith is the pouring into the heart a ſpirit of Faith] a diſpoſition or ſpirit to believe. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 13.</p>
               <p>Hence followeth, 1. The heart is affected towards Chriſt as the giver of life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 10. 2. Comes to Chriſt for life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 37. and this is by means of the covenant of grace which containeth the promiſe of life to believers. The Law is a means remotely to prepare for ſaith, but the Goſpel nextly as it contains the covenant of grace. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 2. </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:51"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:52"/>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:46814:52"/> 3. And thus the ſoul is joyned to Chriſt as its head] 1. Chriſt propounds himſelf as a moſt ſuitable husband, and Match for the ſoul. 2, The ſoul conſenteth. 3. By conſent is joyned to Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17.</p>
               <p>But con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ing the ſalvation of Infants we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some Infants are ſaved, otherwiſe all that dye in their infancy are deſtroyed, which would be a cruel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10. 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All that are ſaved muſt be ſaved by Chriſt, if one might be ſaved without Chriſt, then not needfull for any one whomeſoever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All who are ſaved by Chriſt, muſt be ſaved by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to Chriſt, otherwiſe cannot have communion with him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This union to Chriſt muſt be by faith, for there is no other union to Chriſt revealed in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Faith is wrought either mediately by means of the Goſpel revealing the Covenant of grace, or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately without this Goſpel revelation, but thoſe Infants whom Chriſt ſaveth are not capable of hearing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the Goſpel preached, and yet let it not be hard for us to believe they may be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the firſt Adam could convey of his ſinful image, to his Seed, ſurely the ſecond Adam the Lord Jeſus can communicate of his image.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Have Infants a union to the firſt Adam by natural generation or propagation, and ſhall not ſome Infants have union to the ſecond Adam in the way of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſurely Chriſt hath as much power to ſave Infants as Adam had to deſtroy them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is Communion with Chriſt mystically conſidered?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Communion with Chriſt is that whereby Chriſt doth communicate unto a believer a ſtate of life, and makes him partaker of life it ſelf, and thus hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46814:53"/> with Chriſt: not only relatively in Juſtification and Adoption, but by real communication in ſanctification and glorification.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A believer having union to Chriſt hath communion with Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 32.</item>
                  <item>2. Hence communion. 1. In reſpect of the ſtate of life. 2. In life itſelf, and thus is tranſlated from death to life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt is communion relatively in Juſtification, Adoption.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. He that was condemned is now abſolved in Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</item>
                  <item>2. He that was a ſtranger from God, yea, an Enemy, is become a friend, yea, a child of God in Adoption.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The ſecond is communion by way of real communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as the former reſpects condition, ſo this reſpects diſpoſition. And this is in ſanctification and glorification.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that was filthy and under the power of ſin is cleanſed from filth, and under the dominion of grace] ſin mortified, and the Soul quickned to newneſs of life, thus in ſanctification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that was ſeperated from God, and ſuffering the puniſhment of ſin, doth enjoy God in a bleſſed manner, thus in glorification.] The Soul is matched and joyned to Chriſt in a holy marriage Covenant in vocation, acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Treſpaſſes &amp; debts in Juſtification, accepted into near relation to the King of Kings in Adoption, cloathed with royal apparel, the image of God in ſanctification, admitted to be in the gracious preſence of God, to enjoy him in glorification.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Juſtification?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Juſtification is that whereby the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt being imputed to a believer, and by Faith ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, God is reconciled to him, and he is abſolved from the guilt of ſin, and pronounced righteous and worthy of eternal life, in and for the ſake of Chriſt. </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:53"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:54"/>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:46814:54"/> 1. By Juſtification the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and applyed; that is, of God's part imputed to a believer, reckoned to him to be his own, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 5. and applyed to himſelf by faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 2, 3, 4, 5. hence a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever is juſtified by faith inſtrumentally, hence not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified before faith, hence not juſtified from all eternity; for before faith the wrath of God abides upon him. <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſts righteouſneſs being imputed and applyed to a believer, hence,</p>
               <p n="1">1. God is reconciled to him, ſo that he hath</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Peace with God, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 27. 4</item>
                  <item>Peace with the creatures. <hi>Job.</hi> 5 23.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And he is abſolved from guilt, and pronounced righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and worthy of life in Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 33. 34. This Sentence of Juſtification is declared in the word of God, whether the ſoul doth ſee it or not, for his comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>John.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Adoption?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Adoption is that whereby a believer is advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be a child of God, and to the priviledges of a Son.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He is advanced to be a child of God] 1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 3. 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence advanced to the priviledges of a Son] 1. Hence related to the Father, who hath given him his Son and all other good things, an intereſt in a child's portion. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 32. 2. Hence related to the Son of God as a Brother, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 11, 12. hence a co-heir, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17. hence a King, a Prieſt, a Prophet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 6. And a right to the inheritance it ſelf, the Kingdome of glory, and to creatures in this life, and the miniſtration of Angels. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence related to the Holy Ghoſt, his aſſiſtance, which as its immutable, is called a Seal, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 13, 14. 2. As its a pledg of more, its called an Earneſt of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, 3. As it reſembleth the Aſſiſtance of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which Chriſt hath, ſo its a kingly, prieſtly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46814:55"/> Spirit which a believer enjoyeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 6. 4. As this Spirit doth diſpoſe a Believer to act in a child-like, and filial manner is called a ſpirit of Adoption. <hi>Rom.</hi> 815.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Sanctification?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sanctification is that whereby a believer is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to live to God by Chriſts ſanctifying his nature here in ſome degree, by mortifying vicious diſpoſitions which is the putting off the image of the firſt Adam; and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating gracious principles which is the putting on the image of the ſecond Adam, and in the life to come wholly and perfectly ſanctifyed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A believer is fitted to live unto God, 2] <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 21. called ſanctification, as it maketh holy, a transformation, as it changeth nature, not in reſpect of the Eſſence of the Soul, or Faculties, for it remains the ſame Soul and Faculties; otherwiſe, not the ſame perſon, but the change is in reſpect of qualities, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2. called the image of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> a divine nature, as it inclineth to imitate God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
               <p>In this we may conſider the parts and ſubject.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The parts. 1. A mortifying of vicious diſpoſitions, called the putting off the image of the firſt Adam, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 49. and called mortification, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An ingenerating gracious diſpoſitions, called the putting on the image of the ſecond Adam, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 49. &amp; is vivification, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. in the firſt the virtue of Chriſts death is applyed, in the ſecond, the virtue of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and both theſe by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſubject of this, the whole man, not wholly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The whole man. 1. The underſtanding fitted to diſcern rules which lead unto God, hence principles of ſpiritual wiſdome and ſanctifyed reaſon, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 5, 6. but yet this is only in part, and imperfect, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. ſome abiding ignorance and Atheiſme.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The will fitted to chuſe and cloſe with God as the chiefeſt good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25. hence a principle of love and
<pb facs="tcp:46814:55"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:56"/>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:46814:56"/> life, and yet with ſome reluctancy, not perfectly willing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21. 18, 19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The affections, with the body and members of it fitted to obey the commands of ſanctifyed Reaſon and will, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 13. and yet not perfectly, ſome affections yet remain to be crucified, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hence a perfection in parts, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 23. that is, in all parts and Faculties, every ſanctifying grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not a perfection in degrees, hence 1. Sin and grace in the ſame Faculty, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17. Spirit and fleſh. 2. Hence the combate. 1. <hi>The Fleſh warreth againſt the Spirit,</hi> guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Satan and the World. 2, <hi>The Spirit warreth againſt the Fleſh,</hi> guarded. 1. By the Father, as he pitieth his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm children, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 13. 2. By Chriſt Jeſus, as he is touched with the ſenſe of infirmities of believers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. 3. By the Spirit, as he helpeth their infirmities, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. cauſing believers dayly to repent and convert, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 3. and hence all the ſpiritual armour put on, but above all to <hi>be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</hi> Eph. 6. 11, 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is glorification?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Glorification ſtands in the bleſſed viſion and enjoyment of God himſelf, and all things appertaining to a bleſſed life, of the beginnings of which a believer partaketh in this life, and the perfection of it when the Soul is departed out of the body, and aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Soul and body ſhall be reunited and glorified together at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>In glorification we may conſider 1. The Eſſence of it. 2. The complement.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Eſſence of it ſtands in bleſſed viſions and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The complement of it, all good things belonging to a bleſſed life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 11. it is called glorification, as it maketh believers glorious, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 30.</p>
               <p>The degrees of this, Inchoation and Perfection.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:46814:57"/> 1. Inchoation, here ſome beginnings of it, 1. In di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect actings upon God, ſeeing him as in the glaſs of his word and Ordinances, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. 2. Reflect acts, a believer hath diſcerning what God hath done for him in working in him repentance and ſaith; hence an Aſſurance, that he was elected, and that he was to be for ever happy, hence Joy, <hi>Rom</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Perfection, 1. Of the ſoul immediately after its departure out of the body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. 2. Of the ſoul and body both glorified at the day of Judgement. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4 13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 20. 21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 23.</p>
               <p>Hitherto of internal and myſtical union to and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, proper to believers, now of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and viſible union to and communion with Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is viſible union to and communion with Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Viſible union to, and communion with Chriſt, is that whereby believers doe viſibly profeſs the Faith, and ſubject to the viſible government of Chriſt, having viſible communion with Chriſt in his ordinances, and thus the Church conſidered as viſible doth, in which thoſe who have only and nothing but a viſible union to &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, are Hypocrites.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A viſible profeſſing of the faith] having and holding forth ſo much knowledge of Chriſt as may let Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoul, not groſly and ſottiſhly ignorant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Doe ſubject to the viſible Government of Chirſt in his Ordinances] <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44. 5. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 8. And thus to the judgement of rational charity are viſible Saints, they profeſs this in words, and their works do not deny it. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
               <p>And viſible Saints may be conſidered in a ſegregative, or a congregative manner.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Segregatively, as ſcatter'd ſheep by themſelves, as thoſe certain diſciples ſcatter'd, <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Congregatively, as flocking together, and thus a
<pb facs="tcp:46814:57"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:58"/>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:46814:58"/> Church as a viſible body doth. But thoſe who have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an external and viſible union and communion with Chriſt, but not internally, myſtically and ſincerely, theſe are Hypocrites. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 13. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is a viſible Church?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A viſible Church is a company of viſible Saints joyned in a viſible covenant with Chriſt and one with another, to walk together in the uſe of Chriſts Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a viſible Church order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is a viſible Church is manifeſt, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Chriſt hath no viſible Body, no viſible Officers, or they to officiate to them who are not viſible, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The matter of a viſible Church is viſible Saints, for Chriſt's viſible Church is called his Body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. his Temple, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 21, 22. therefore the matter of this ought not to be viſible Rebels and Traitors.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The form of a viſible Church is their covenanting, 1. There is ſuch a covenant, for the covenant ſo often mentioned with the Iſraelites. 1. It was not the covenant of works, for that was made only with our firſt Parents, and with us in Adam, but ſince mans fall who could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in that. 2. Not the covenant of grace ſtrictly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for believe and live, for many were in the covenant ſpoken of made with the Church of the Jews, who were never in the covenant of grace, but were graceleſs, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11. 10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet this belongs to the covenant of grace as an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance appointed by it, and an outward means to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this is a form of the viſible Church appeareth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>1. They are a City and Corporation, therefore a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to make them ſuch. 2. They joyne in holy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip either without conſent or with conſent, if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent, then though a Church be unwilling, they cannot keep them out, then they cannot caſt them out,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:46814:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> though they ought to keep out the unworthy, and to caſt out the obſtinate offender.</p>
               <p>If by conſent, then it is either manifeſt or unknown conſent, if an unknown conſent be ſufficient to admiſſion then an unknown diſſent may be ſufficient to keep out, or caſt out; and if a manifeſt conſent be neceſſary to a joyning in Church fellowſhip, then a covenant, for what is a Church covenant, but a manifeſt conſent to walk with Chriſt, and one with another, according to the rules of the Goſpel in viſible Church order.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may a viſible Church be conſidered?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A viſible Church may be conſidered in reſpect of the time in which it lived. 1. As it was confined to a Family from Adams time to Moſes time, and then they had Prophets to be extraordinary Rulers, and the Head of the Family was the ordinary Ruler, and the rule of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was given by Tradition.</p>
               <p>A viſible Church may be conſidered either as <hi>totum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneum,</hi> or <hi>Integrale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As <hi>totum homogeneum,</hi> and thus is diſtributed into individual Congregations and Churches, as mankind in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Individual men, and thus every individual Church hath the matter and form of a Church, and thus we read of the Churches of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or as <hi>totum Integrale,</hi> or an individual man made up of his members, and ſo every individual Church doth conſiſt of its members, and in this ſenſe comes in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of a Church, as <hi>Organicum totum,</hi> as fitted for operations for the good of the whole.</p>
               <p>And hence Governours, and governed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Governours, who exerciſe Authority over the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurch, having the Eccleſiaſtical <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> doctrinal, Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial. 1. Doctrinal diſpenſation of the Word, as Church Officers, and of the Sacraments, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 10, 11. the adminiſtration of theſe committed to Church-Officers.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:59"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:60"/>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:46814:60"/> 2. Judicially by the Officers, with the conſent of the Church. 1. In reſpect of thoſe without. 2. And within. 1. Without. 1. Some to be taken in by opening. 2. Some to be kept out by ſhutting the dore of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of thoſe within, to bind, looſen. 1. To bind, the firſt degree of which is admonition, the ſecond degree is excommunication, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p>The Miniſterial Rulers of the Church, who act in the name of Chriſt the ſupream Ruler and Head of the Church, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 18. theſe are extraordinary, ordinary.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Extraordinary, called of God immediately, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 1. and had infallible direction and inſpiration from God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 1, 2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Ordinary Rulers called of God mediately by the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. hence Election and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. and theſe ought to rule according to the Word given by the extraordinary Rulers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The governed is the Church, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. and may be conſidered in reſpect of the time in which it lived. 1. In a Family, from Adams time to Moſes time, ſome Prophets were Rulers, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Jude</hi> 14. 2. The Head of the Family was the ordinary Ruler, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. the eldeſt Son, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. 5. <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 12. 14.</p>
               <p>And then the Rule of Religion was given by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, it was not written until Moſes time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How was it with the Church in Moſes time?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Church in Moſes time and afterwards was in and confined to the people of Iſrael, who had their great congregation, and inferior congregations, the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, and their extraordinary Rulers were Prophets, ſome of them wrote the old Teſtament: and their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Rulers were the high Prieſt, inferior Prieſts and Levites, and the Rulers of the Synagogues, and of this Church Chriſt came typed out in ceremonies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Moſes time and afterwards the Church was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:46814:61"/> to the people of Iſrael, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 6. in which we may conſider their congregation, their priviledge.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Their congregation, their great one, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 10.</item>
                  <item>2. Their inferiour Congregations, their <hi>Synagogues, Pſal.</hi> 79. 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 5.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Rulers, extraordinary, ordinary:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Extraordinary, and were Prophets, ſome of them wrote the old Teſtament, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8. 12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> but the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> was not wrote by them, and therefore is not canonical.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their ordinary Governours, 1. Of their great congregation, the high Prieſt; inferiour, as Prieſts, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 3, 4. 2. Of their leſſer congregations, the Rulers of the Synagogues, <hi>Mar.</hi> 5. 22. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 11. <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The priviledges of this Church, Chriſt came of this Church concerning the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 3, 4, 5. 2. He was promiſed to them by the Prophets, 3. Typed out to them by diverſe ceremonyes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 2. And this Church continued untill Chriſt the Meſſias was ſlain, <hi>Zac</hi> 11. 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 50, 51.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How is it with the Church ſince Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The viſible church is not conſined to any one People, but is amongſt many ſince Chriſts coming, and in its primitive time had the Apoſtles, Evangeliſts and Prophets to be extraordinary Rulers, and ſome of theſe wrote the New-Teſtament; and ſince that time it hath Paſtors, Teachers, Ruling Elders and Deacons to be the ordinary Officers, and hath Chriſt to be the exalted head, the holy Scriptures being perfected.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Church ſince Chriſts coming we may conſider, their Government and priviledges.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Government, Extraordinary, Ordinary.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Extraordinary Rulers, 1. The Apoſtles, who were
<pb facs="tcp:46814:61"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:62"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:62"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:63"/>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:46814:63"/> to preach to all nations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>ult.</hi> And to plant church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6. and to be witneſſes of Chriſts Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Aſcention, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Evangeliſts, who were to aſſiſt the Apoſtles in preaching, and in eſtabliſhing the Churches according to their Doctrine. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3, 4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Prophets, who had ſingular gifts to interpret the ſcriptures, and to foretell things to come, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 24, 25. <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 8, 9, 10. And ſome of theſe extraordinary Rulers wrote the New-Teſtament. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 30. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ordinary Officers are firſt Elders who are either only Ruling, or not only ſo but Teaching as Paſtors, Teachers. <hi>Eph.</hi> 11. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8. Or inferiour Officers, the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Priviledges of this Church,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They have Chriſt already exhibited, the good things typed out are extant, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 70. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence the Members of this Church are evangelical believers. 1. Confeſſing that Chriſt is the ſon of <hi>Mary,</hi> and the ſon of the living God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 34, 35. 2. They doe receive Chriſt as their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted head, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 35. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 9, 10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Church is no longer confined to one people, but amongſt many, hence univerſal and catholick, as ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of all nations, many Churches ſwarmed out of that one church, and firſt church at Jeruſalem. <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 31. and are called churches, the catholick viſible church doth exiſt in theſe individual churches.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This church hath the holy Scriptures perfectly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How doe you prove the Holy Scriptures to be the Word of God?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The holy Scriptures are proved to be the word of God by the teſtimony of the godly in all ages, and by divine teſtimony, the miracles wrought, and the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Spirit of God in the Saints, and by many arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial arguments, becauſe they doe reveal divine wiſdome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:46814:64"/> holineſs, Juſtice, mercy, with moſt perfect harmony &amp; wonderfull efficacy, containing a perfect rule of Faith and obedience.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures are proved to be the word of God by Arguments, inartificial, artificial,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Inartificial, namely teſtimony, humane, divine.</p>
               <p>1. Humane, the teſtimony of the godly in all ages, firſt in the primitive times, their preachers expounded theſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 2, 11. 2. Chriſtians converted by theſe, 3. Many ſuffered for the defence of theſe. 4. Their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, <hi>Romanes, Jews, Phariſes, Sadduces,</hi> Heriticks, could not deny but that ſuch Doctrines were taught by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15, 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Teſtimony is delivered down to us, witneſs 1. The many ancient Records of many hiſtories and councils. 2. The ancient Records of many Countryes, Nations, Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South. 3. The many Chriſtians in the ſeveral Ages who have ſuffered for the defence of theſe, and the Hereticks have pleaded theſe Scriptures, although they have perverted them, let us conſider the validity of the former Teſtimony.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It hath a moral certainty, as certain as man can be, that he was born of ſuch Parents, and hath a right to ſuch an Inheritance which depends upon humane Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In ſome reſpect this Teſtimony hath an infallible certainty. 1. Otherwiſe theſe witneſſes would have contradicted themſelves, they living at ſo great a diſtance one from another, and in ſeveral Ages could not meet together to invent a deluſion to deceive their Poſterity. 2. Otherwiſe Adverſaries would have contradicted them as <hi>de facto,</hi> and have ſaid, that no ſuch doctrines were taught by the Apoſtles, hence this humane Teſtimony as it is circumſtanced is binding, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. 1, 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 32.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Divine Teſtimony external and internal. </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:64"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:65"/>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:46814:65"/> 1. External by Miracles, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. called Gods witneſſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 4. 2. Inward Teſtimony, the Spirit of God in a believer witneſſing, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Artificial Arguments. 1. They reveal wiſdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the inventions of men or Angels, the Myſtery of the Trinity, and mans Recovery, and many other Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. 2. Moſt beautiful holineſs ſhining in theſe Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 140. 3. Juſtice giving to God and man his due, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 12. 4. Moſt rich mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 20. 5. Moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect harmony, though wrote by diverſe, in diverſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and diverſe languages, full of predictions and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, yet they all agree. 6. Their duration, 1. Were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore other Writings. 2. Do continue and ſhall to the end of the World, <hi>Ier.</hi> 6. 16. <hi>Math.</hi> 28. <hi>ult.</hi> 7. The Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Iſai</hi> 55. 11. 8. The perfection of them, they contain a perfect Rule of Faith and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 1, 2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 19. Either theſe Scriptures were invented by God or by ſome creature, not by ſome creature, for if by ſome creature, it was either by ſome good or evil creature, not by ſome good creature, for no good man or Angel would invent a thing, and then ſay it was Gods invention, not by ſome evil creature, for the holy Scriptures are contrary to the wicked, therefore it is apparent theſe Scriptures are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by God himſelf.</p>
               <p>Hitherto of Faith, next concerning Obſervance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Obſervance?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Obſervance is the ſecond part of Religion, and ſtands in performance of duty to God, by obeying his Law, which is a Platform of acting for God, and he hath made it known to us for that end.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſervance is a ſecond part of Religion. 1. It is a part of Religion, without which Religion is vain. 2. And a ſecond part performed by Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 10, 20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It ſtands in performance of duty to God, as God is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46814:66"/> our Creator, Redeemer, and Comforter, <hi>Math.</hi> 28. 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This performance of duty is by obeying his Law, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. 8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Law of God is the Platform of well acting, and acting for God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 15.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hence made known for this end. 1. The firſt Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this was in the heart of man at firſt, a fair inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it upon man at firſt, he being made according to the Image of God in holineſs and righteouſneſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 29.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some reliques of it in fallen man, ſo much as may teſtifie that man was made to be Religious, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15. hence Conſcience witneſſing in reſpect of God, and a Judge in reſpect of man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Law was renewed to the Church of the Jews by a lively voice, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and becomes uſeful. 1. To diſcover ſin, and to drive the Soul to Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 24. 2. After a believer is in Chriſt the Law is uſeful to him as a Rule of obedience, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 17. 3. But a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers obedience being imperfect it cannot merit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 4. but is accepted for the ſake of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How is obedience distributed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Obedience is diſtributed into love to God, and love to man, love to God being a reſpect to God, nextly and directly as he is God, and may be called worſhip.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Obedience may be divided into love to God and love to man, <hi>Math.</hi> 22. 37, 38, 39.</item>
                  <item>2. Love to God is a reſpect nextly and directly to God as he is God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 21. and it is called worſhip, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 21.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is that worſhip in the firſt Command requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The worſhip in the firſt Command required is,
<pb facs="tcp:46814:66"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:67"/>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:46814:67"/> to take the true God alone to be our God, cleaving to him in underſtanding, will and affections, and the expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions of the outward man, being ſuitable to that inward worſhip.</p>
               <p>The Commandments of the firſt Table do enjoyne divine worſhip, in which we may conſider the kinds of worſhip, and the manners of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The kinds of worſhip. 1. Natural. 2. Inſtituted.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Natural worſhip, not that it is natural to corrupt nature to perform it, but becauſe the light of Reaſon and natural Conſcience may convince us that worſhip is due to God, namely, 1. That there is but one true God. 2. That we ought to take him to be our God. 3. And therefore to cleave to him, and honour him as God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 21 and this kind of worſhip is required in the firſt Command.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To take the true God alone to be our God, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 28. 9. <hi>Math.</hi> 22. 37. 2. Hence a cleaving to God. 1. In underſtanding, which is that whereby the underſtanding having received the light of the knowledge of his glory is ſatisfied with his wiſdome, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 33. 2. Hence a cleaving of the will to God, which is that whereby the will makes choice of God, and is ſatisfied with him, and therefore acts from him and for him.</p>
               <p>1. The will doth chuſe God above all, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25. 2. Is ſatisfied in him as its portion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 5. 3. acts from him and for him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From him. 1. In ſtaying upon him for all good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. 9. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50. 10. 2. In pouring out the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 8. 2. acting for him. 1. In ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to, being filled with, and acted by his will, <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 12. willing his glory, and loſing all our ends in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 36.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence a cleaving of the affections to God, the will being affected with love to God, and hates that which diſpleaſeth him.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:46814:68"/> 1. Love to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 1. from this love floweth. 1. Patient hope for God, and deſire after him, and a joy and delight in him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A hoping for God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 7, 8. and that patiently, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 1. 2. A deſire after him, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26. 8. 3. A joying in him, and that which it enjoyes of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hates that which diſpleaſeth him. From this hatred floweth a fear and abomination of ſin and ſorrow becauſe of it, with holy anger. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A fear, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> 1. An abomination of the evil of ſin, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 43. 3. A ſorrow with an holy anger, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11. and thus of the inward worſhip required in the firſt Command.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The expreſſions of the outward man ought to be ſuitable to this inward worſhip, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 41. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 14, 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is that worſhip required in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſecond Command doth require inſtituted worſhip, (namely) an attendance upon God in all his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as in Prayer, hearing, reading his Word, and celebration of Sacraments, and joyning to a viſible Church, where Church diſcipline by Church Officers is exerciſed with the conſent of the Church.</p>
               <p>The Worſhip required in the ſecond Command is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Worſhip, that is, the worſhip which without ſome revelation out of the Word of God, that God hath inſtituted it, we could not find it out, and otherwiſe our worſhip is vain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. 9. yea Devil-worſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 10.</p>
               <p>Theſe means of worſhip are either, Prime or firſt, or in order to thoſe,</p>
               <p>The Prime, 1. Hearing and reading the word of God, and to which alſo belongeth Repetition of the word, and Chriſtian conference, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 1. 2. Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, Baptiſme <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. The
<pb facs="tcp:46814:68"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:69"/>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:46814:69"/> Lords Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24, 25. 3. Praying with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Prayer, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe Ordinances which are in order to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. 1. A viſible Church, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 17. 2. Church Officers, Eph, 4. 11, 12. 3. Church Diſcipline, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 18, 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt,</hi> What doth the third Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A worſhipping of God with all meet Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, reſpecting both the Attributes of God and his Name, which he hath put upon all his Ordinances, and therefore to prepare for them, and to behave our ſelves reverently in the time of the diſpenſation of them, and after the uſe of them to bring forth ſuitable fruit.</p>
               <p>The two former Commands reſpect the kinds of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, next of the manners of worſhip, moſt reverent, and ſolemn.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Reverent, this the third Command requireth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 7.</p>
               <p>The Name of God is that whereby God hath made known himſelf, as his Attributes and Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Attributes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 19. and the Reverence reſpecting his Attributes is that whereby we take heed of a vain mentioning his Attributes, or being too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent or familiar in uſing them, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 2. and that we practically ſhew forth his praiſes and virtues, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His divine Ordinances, upon which he hath put his Name, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 5. and the Reverence reſpecting theſe ſtands 1. In preparation for them, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. 2, in the time of the diſpenſation of them to behave our ſelves reverently with a reverent delight, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. 13. and in a comely and orderly manner, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 40. 3. And after the uſe of them that we retain the ſavour of them, and bring forth the fruit of them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 21. <hi>Col</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Math.</hi> 21. 43.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:46814:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the fourth Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The fourth Command requireth to ſanctifie a ſeventh part of the week, which was the laſt of ſeven, from Creation until Chriſts Reſurrection, but ought to be the firſt of ſeven from Chriſts Reſurrection, until the laſt day.</p>
               <p>In this we may conſider the ſanctification <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſelf, and the day to be ſanctified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How ought we to ſanctifie the Sabbath?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ought to ſanctifie the Sabbath by reſting from our own works, that is all ſuch works as are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther works of mercy, nor neceſſity; nor have any direct reſpect to the comely ſanctifying of the day, and to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the time unto the Lord by attendance of divine worſhip in publick, in the Family, and in ſecret.</p>
               <p>In ſanctifying a Sabbath there ought to be a reſt, and a ſanctifying our reſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A reſting from our own works, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. 13. hence to reſt from ſuch works as are not works of mercy, nor neceſſity, <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 7. nor ſuch works as have no direct reſpect to the ſanctifying of the day, <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſanctifying our reſt by attendance upon Gods worſhip in publick, in Family, and in ſecret, for they were to attend the dayly offerings appointed for every day, and beſides the continual offerings, they were to bring the Sabbath offering, <hi>Numb.</hi> 28. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 92. 1. <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7.</p>
               <p>And hence we ought to prepare for the Sabbath by a timely calling off our thoughts and actions from worldly occaſions, and to call them in, and to go forth and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the holy day approaching, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. 13. and after the Sabbath is ended, not greedily nor ſuddenly ruſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to worldly occaſions, as if we were weary of the Sabbath, and glad it were at an end.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:70"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:71"/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:46814:71"/> Concerning the day to be ſanctified let us conſider,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How doe you prove that we ought in theſe Gospel dayes to keep a weekly Sabbath?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt becauſe Chriſt taught his Diſciples to pray, that their flight might not be on the Sabbath, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 25. If no Sabbath then it was needleſs for Chriſts Diſciples to pray that their flight might not be on the Sabbath, but Chriſt ſaw it needfull to leave this inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with his Diſciples, becauſe the Sabbath ſhould as certainly continue as the winter, and as they were to pray that their flight might not be in the winter, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that it might not be on the Sabbath day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How doe you prove this in the ſecond place, that in Gospel dayes we ought to keep a Sabbath?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt came not to deſtroy the moral Law, but to fullfill it.</p>
               <p>If no Sabbath, then Chriſt hath deſtroyed ſome part of the moral law, but this cannot be. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How do you prove that we ought not to keep the ſeventh day of the week a Christian Sabbath?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe God's reſt in the ſeventh day from the work's of Creation, was ſpoyled by the ſin of man, and another reſt by Chriſt the Redeemer, and another day came which doth remain.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God reſted in the ſeventh day from the works of Creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 1, 2. and in the fourth Command it is expreſt to be the Reaſon of ſanctifying the ſeventh day of the week.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This reſt was ſpoyled by the ſin of man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 6, 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another reſt came from the work of Redemption, and another day of reſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 4, 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:46814:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How do you prove this in the ſecond place that the ſeventh day ſince Chriſts Reſurrection ought not to be kept for a Sabbath?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe to keep the ſeventh day of the week was the doctrine of falſe Teachers, and is contrary to the doctrine ond practice of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who did advance the firſt day of the week above any other day.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10. The Apoſtle reproved the falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for teaching the Galatians to obſerve dayes, Moneths, and years, according to the Law of Moſes, by dayes is meant that which is leſs then Moneths, and therefore to be underſtood of weekly Sabbaths, and yet not of the Chriſtian Sabbath; for thoſe Teachers ſtood for that which is according to Moſes his Miniſtry, and in <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. the Apoſtle condemns holy dayes, new Moons, and Sabbaths. Holy dayes are mentioned as greater then new Moons, and therefore are meant of Annual Sabbatical dayes, and Sabbath dayes as leſs then new Moons, and therefore to be underſtood of the weekly Sabbaths the Jews kept.</p>
               <p>And that the Apoſtles did advance the firſt day of the week to be the Chriſtian Sabbath, will appear in the next place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How doth it appear by the doctrine and practice of the Apoſtles that we ought to keep the firſt day of the week a Chriſtian Sabbath.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe that day of the week which is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above other dayes, by the Name of the Lords day, as he is the Redeemer, this cannot be underſtood of the ſeventh day which is God's day, as he was Creator, much leſs of other dayes, but only of the firſt day of the week in which Chriſt had glorious reſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. One day is honoured by the Name of the Lords
<pb facs="tcp:46814:72"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:46814:73"/> day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 10. for the ſcope of the Apoſtle is ſet down, the particular time when he had that Viſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is called the Lord's day by that great Goſpel Apoſtle John, who ſpeaketh in a Goſpel ſenſe, and that in the ſame ſenſe as the Lords Supper, and the Lords Table, that which was ſanctifyed by the inſtitution of Chriſt the Redeemer, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 21. and as he was Lord of the Sabbath, <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This cannot be meant of the ſeventh day, for that is not the day of the Lord as a Redeemer, but as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But is meant of the firſt day of the week, in which Chriſt reſted from his heavy and hard labour in the ſtate of humiliation, and roſe from the dead, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 1. and in which day he having received all power in Heaven and on Earth, appeared to his Diſciples, 19. <hi>ver.</hi> and in which day he communicated the holy Ghoſt unto his Diſciples, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. the day of the glorious reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How do you prove this in the ſecond place?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the Apoſtle did command all the Churches on the firſt day of the week to prepare their Collection for the Saints, a moſt eminent duty of the Sabbath, and thus did advance the firſt day of the week above any other day, not by humane Inſtitution, that is unlawful, but by divine Inſtitution, becauſe of the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this day.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtle did command not only the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> but Churches at <hi>Galatia</hi> to have in readineſs their Collections for the Saints in the firſt day of the week, is expreſt in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this is a moſt eminent duty of the Sabbath is manifeſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 6, 7, 8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The firſt day of the week was either a common and indifferent day, or a ſpecial and holy day, if a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:46814:74"/> and indifferent day, then the Apoſtle ought not to make that to be neceſſary by impoſing an Injunction and Command upon it which God hath made indifferent, hence ought not to have ordered, and by order com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to attend ſuch a work of mercy in the firſt day of the week, if that day were but a common and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different day, this would be to eſteem one common day above another, contrary to his own doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1, 5. and therefore it was becauſe the firſt day of the week was the holy day, a Chriſtian Sabbath by divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How do you prove this in the third place?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it was the uſual practice of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples, in the primitive times, and of the Witneſſes of Chriſt in all Ages ſince that time, to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the firſt day of the week for divine worſhip, and this was not becauſe it would be more expedient time, for them, but becauſe it is the day of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
               <q>Thus we read in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 7.</q>
               <p n="1">1. Of the aſſembling of the Diſciples, not only ſome few, but of the generality of them, it is ſpoken in the general.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They aſſembled to break bread, it is not meant of a love Feaſt, that was unlawful in a publick Church-meeting, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 34. but is to be underſtood of the Lords Supper, neither was it to hear Paul preach, but it is ſaid, they came together to break bread, and Paul preached, ſo that he took this ſeaſon to preach to them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was their uſual practice to aſſemble for divine worſhip in this day, and therefore it is ſaid when they came together, and thus of Chriſtians in all Ages ſince the primitive time.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:46814:75"/> 4. Their meeting in the firſt day of the week was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe it was a more expedient time for them then ſome other day, or becauſe it was a ſpecial day, and the Chriſtian Sabbath, not becauſe it was more expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for them, if the ſeventh day was kept as a Sabbath, how could it be expedient or lawful to defer admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacrament on the ſeventh day, and to meet again the next day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Doth not the change of the Sabbath from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day to the firſt day aboliſh the fourth Command?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In no wiſe, for, the Reaſon of the ſeventh dayes being taken away, and a Reaſon of the ſame kind, but of a greater degree: for the firſt day of the week be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come in the place of it, the fourth Command by this means in the ſcope of it is eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Reaſon why the ſeventh day was ſanctified was becauſe God reſted from the works of Creation, but this reſt was ſpoyled by the ſin of man, and the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented that he had made man, and other Creatures cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the ſin of man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 6, 7. conſequently the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Sabbath day was taken away.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A reaſon of the ſame kind, but of a greater degree, for the firſt day of the week came in the place of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, for Chriſt had wrought a new Creation by his death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 15, 17. and as <hi>he is the firſt born of every Creature, by whom all things conſiſt; and that by the blood of his Croſs he might reconcile all things to himſelf, whether things in Earth, or in Heaven,</hi> 1 Col. 15, 16, 17. but this of a greater degree, for this new Creation is a greater work then the firſt Creation; Chriſt's work as Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is greater then the work of Creation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 20, 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. 9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The fourth Command by this means is eſtabliſhed in the ſcope of it. for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The change of the Sabbath from the ſeventh day
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:46814:76"/> of the week to the firſt day ſtands upon the ſame ground and bottom upon which the ſeventh day was ſanctified, namely, becauſe of the Lords reſting from his works of Creation, but behold he reſteth from the works of the new Creation, and by which a reſtoration of that which was ſpoyled by mans ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The change of the Sabbath from the ſeventh to the firſt day, doth moſt admirably attain the end God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in ſanctifying a Sabbath. 1. God intended his glory in the works of Creation; but by the Chriſtian Sabbath, he hath the glory of his works of Creation and Redemption, a greater glory then the former. 2. God intended the good of man, <hi>Mark</hi> 2. 27, 28. 1. In reſpect of mans body, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 14. that it may reſt a ſeventh part of the week, this end is as well attained in the firſt day of the week as on the ſeventh day. 2. In reſpect of mans Soul, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 12. that the Soul of man may have a ſolemn time for the worſhip of God, but to do this in remembrance of the work of Redemption, is more for the Soul's good of man then to do it in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the work of Creation, ſo the ſanctifying of the firſt day of the week for this end, is more for the good of the Soul of man then to ſanctifie the ſeventh day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence it is no aboliſhing of the fourth Command, but a fulfilling and eſtabliſhing it; as the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand requireth that the means of worſhip, &amp; thoſe only which God appointeth ſhould be obſerved, he inſtituted to her means of worſhip to the Jews then now in Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel times, and other means of worſhip in the Goſpel dayes then before Chriſts coming, yet both they and we by virtue of the ſecond Command were required to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the means of worſhip, and the change of means of worſhip from that which it was before Goſpel times, doth not cauſe any change of the ſecond Command: So the fourth Command requireth to ſanctifie that Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb facs="tcp:46814:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:46814:77"/> which God appointeth. When God required the ſeventh day it was to be ſanctifyed by virtue of the fourth Command, and ſince he hath required the firſt day day of the week, it ought to be kept by virtue of the fourth Command, and yet no change of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; Will any be ſo bold to ſay that God himſelf could not change the day; ſeeing the Sabbath was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for man, <hi>and the Son of man is Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> Mark 2. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Hitherto of love to God, next of love to man.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is that love to man the Law requireth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Law requireth to love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf for the ſake of God, and this containeth all the duties of the ſecond Table, <hi>Math.</hi> 22. 39. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the fifth Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The fifth Command requireth to preſerve the honour of thy Neighbour, and therefore to behave thy ſelf reverently to Superiours, honour being due to them above thy ſelf, reſpectively to equals, honour being due to them equal to thy ſelf, and not contemning thy infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 1, 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 1, 2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the ſixth Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſixth Command requireth to preſerve the life of thy Neighbour, and therefore to behave thy ſelf meekly, patiently, peaceably, and merciful towards him, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18, 20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the ſeventh Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſeventh Command requireth Chaſtity,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:46814:78"/> (that is) purity in all things reſpecting the generating of mankind, and therefore to behave thy ſelf modeſtly and gravely, obſerving all things becoming purity, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 3, 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the eighth Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The eighth Command requireth to preſerve the goods of thy Neighbour, and therefore to behave thy ſelf juſtly and equally in ſeeking after, keeping and uſing worldly goods <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 28. <hi>Gol.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 31.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the ninth Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ninth Command requireth to preſerve the Name of thy Neighbour, and therefore to have (in your Aſſertions and Promiſes (a reſpect truly and faithfully to the Truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 2, 3, 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth the tenth Command require?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The tenth Command requireth to preſerve the proſperity of thy Neighbour, and therefore a conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with thine own things, and not envying another, 3 <hi>Epiſt. Joh.</hi> 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto of Obedience, next concerning helps to Obedience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are ſpecial helps to Obedience</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Prayer, and the Sacraments of the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Prayer?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Prayer is a Religious preſenting of our deſires before God, by Confeſſion, Petition, and Thanksgiving, according to the will of God, ſometimes with others, and
<pb facs="tcp:46814:78"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:79"/>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:46814:79"/> ſometimes alone as in ſecret, and to Prayer belongeth Religious ſinging.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Prayer is a religious preſenting our deſires before God, called the pouring out of the heart before God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 8. the ſhewing him our trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142. 2. nextly and directly preſented to God, therefore a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſenting our deſires, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57. 1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The parts of Prayer. 1. Confeſſion of our ſinful unworthineſs, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 4. 2. Petitioning for mercy and grace in the Name of Chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 24. 3. Thanksgiving for mercy received, or that we hope to receive, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Rule of Prayer, it is an asking according to the will of God revealed in his Word, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 14. 1. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his commanding will. 2. According to his promiſing will, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 27.</p>
               <p>And Prayer ought to be, 1. Sometimes with others in publick, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 16. 2. In the Family, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 25. and ſometimes alone in ſecret, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 13, 14. and to Prayer belongs religious ſinging of Pſalms, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are the Sacraments of the New-Teſtament?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Sacraments of the New-Teſtament are Baptiſme and the Lords Supper. Baptiſme a Sacrament of entrance into Covenant with Chriſt, and his Church, and the Lords Supper a Sacrament of our continuance in Covenant and Communion with Chriſt, and his Church. The one cometh in the place of Circumciſion, and is a Goſpel Circumciſion, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 11, 12. The other cometh in the place of the Paſsover, and is our Goſpel Paſsover, <hi>Math.</hi> 26. 17, 18, 24, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 20. 16, 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26, 27.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What followeth hence, that Baptiſme is a ſigne and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:46814:80"/> Seal of entrance into Covenant with Chriſt, and his Church?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That all Church members ought to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and therefore the Infants of Parents in Church ſtate ought to be baptized, for they are in Covenant with Chriſt, and members of his body, and therefore called his Diſciples, and a holy Seed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All Church members ought to be baptized, becauſe they are of the body, therefore to be baptized, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13. if Church members, then the promiſes viſibly belong to them, and therefore the viſible Seal of them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38. 39. the Covenant and the Seal are ſo cloſely conjoyned by God, that the Seal is called the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Infants of Parents in Church ſtate are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Chriſt, for God hath promiſed to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their hearts, and the hearts of their Seed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6. and the promiſes belong to them, and to their Children, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 39. and an Infant whoſe Parents, either both of them, or one of them being in Church ſtate, that Infant is a Church member, called therefore a Diſciple of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 10. thoſe are called Diſciples upon whom the falſe Teachers would have impoſed the yoke of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion according to the Law of Moſes, but theſe were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and theſe are called a holy Seed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What followeth hence in the ſecond place?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Baptiſme ought to be adminiſtred by pouring of water, and ſo waſhing, and not by dipping the body in the water, becauſe it is a Sacrament of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Covenant, in which Chriſt by his Spirit doth apply himſelf to us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Sacrament of Baptiſme is a ſigne and Seal of entrance into Covenant, is plain from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Scriptures in the deſcription of Baptiſme.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Chriſt doth in the Covenant of grace firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to the Soul is clear, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 12. he is firſt in loving us, and cometh to us before we can come to him.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:80"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46814:81"/>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:46814:81"/> 3. Hence that means of adminiſtring of Baptiſme as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt ſuitable to the thing ſignified ought to be attended, but the applying of water to the baptized, this ſignifieth Chriſt by his Spirit applying himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 5. baptized with water, and baptized with the holy Ghoſt, that is baptized by water, and the holy Ghoſt poured out upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 33.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence the body ought not to be dipped into the water, for that would ſignifie that the baptized is firſt applyed to Chriſt, and not Chriſt to him firſtly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 3. buried with Chriſt in Baptiſme. In burying the body there is not a thruſting the body into the duſt or earth, but a caſting of earth upon the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What followeth hence, that the Lords Supper is a Sacrament of continuance in covenant and communion with Chriſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That thoſe only ought to be admitted to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Lords Supper, who doe hold forth Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Faith, with an ability to examine themſelves and diſcern the Lords body; for he that partaketh, before he doth partake of the Lords Supper, he ought to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf and diſcern the Lords body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 28. 29. Hence it followeth,</p>
               <p>1. He ought to have Faith and Repentance before he doth partake; for the Lords Supper is inſtituted, not for Regenaration, but for nouriſhment and confirmation. 2. Repentance and Faith are the matter concerning which the communicant ought to examine himſelf with a diſcerning into the Goſpel ſenſe and miſtery of the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence he that partaketh muſt have this ability thus to examine himſelf, otherwiſe he cannot perform theſe preparatory dutyes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He ought to hold theſe forth, 1. To his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that his own conſcience may not condemn him for preſumptuous partaking. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 23.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:46814:82"/> 2. To hold theſe forth to the judgment of the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, 1. Of the Church Officers, that ſo the Miniſter in the judgment of charity may ſay, <hi>Take, eat, this is the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord Jeſus given for you.</hi> 2. To the judgment of the charity of the Church; for communicants do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to have communion with Chriſt and one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as one body in him. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 15, 16, 17. And it's the duty of the Church and Officers to put the difference between the clean and the unclean, the holy and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, according to their reſpective capacityes. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 7, 8, 23.</p>
               <p>And although Faith be weak and obedience imperfect, and prayers and preparations far ſhort of the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sanctuary Inſtitutions, yet the Lord will pardon and confirm his favour by the Lords Supper to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble believing Soul.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:82"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:46814:83"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:83"/>
            <p> YOU doe take God the only true God to be your God, the Lord Jeſus to be your Saviour, your Prophet, Prieſt and King, and the holy Spirit to be your Sanctifyer and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter.</p>
            <p>Promiſing in his name and ſtrength to cleave to him as your chiefeſt and only good; and by the help of his Spirit and Grace, to walk before him in a faithfull diſcharge of Covenant duties: and in a regular ſubjection to, and obſervation of, all the holy Ordinances and Inſtitutions of Chriſt, of which (at preſent) you are capable, as they ſhall be duly adminiſtred within this Church and Congregation: and to refrain, (and what in you lyeth) to reform all ſin that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereto, eſpecially the provoking and growing ſins of this time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:84"/>
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The Authors abſence from the Preſs, and his Copy being dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficult to read, hath occaſioned many miſtakes, which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reader is deſired thus to correct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 1 <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>r.</hi> a Doctrine. <hi>P</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> arts. <hi>l.</hi> 30. <hi>r.</hi> by Faith. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l</hi> 12 <hi>r.</hi> by Faith. <hi>l.</hi> 22 <hi>r.</hi> unknown good. <hi>p.</hi> 4 <hi>l.</hi> 17 <hi>r.</hi> Truths. <hi>p.</hi> 5 <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>r.</hi> for us. <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>r.</hi> manners. <hi>p.</hi> 8 <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>r.</hi> Pſal. 99. <hi>l.</hi> 19 <hi>r.</hi> theſe are one. <hi>l.</hi> 22 <hi>r.</hi> Pſa. 90. <hi>p.</hi> 12 <hi>l.</hi> 8 <hi>r.</hi> 2. Individual. <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>r. ſpirants. p.</hi> 14 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>r.</hi> for his. <hi>p.</hi> 15 <hi>l.</hi> 8 <hi>r.</hi> rational. <hi>p.</hi> 19 <hi>l.</hi> 22 <hi>r.</hi> water. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 33. <hi>r</hi> man. <hi>p.</hi> 24 <hi>l.</hi> 22 <hi>r.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 25 <hi>r.</hi> 4. <hi>p</hi> 29 <hi>l.</hi> 32 <hi>r.</hi> act under. <hi>p.</hi> 30 <hi>l.</hi> 27 <hi>r.</hi> to man. <hi>p.</hi> 34 <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>r. John</hi> 3. 34. <hi>p.</hi> 45 <hi>l.</hi> 29 <hi>r. Act.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>l.</hi> 4 <hi>r.</hi> 2 Cor. <hi>p.</hi> 51 <hi>l.</hi> 9 <hi>r.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 54. <hi>l.</hi> 25 <hi>r.</hi> as an Individual. <hi>p.</hi> 54 <hi>l.</hi> 32 <hi>r.</hi> Keyes. <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>r. Act.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 6 <hi>r. Pſa.</hi> 74 <hi>p.</hi> 57 <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>r. Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 60 <hi>l.</hi> 5 <hi>r. Pſal.</hi> 119. 152. <hi>p.</hi> 61 <hi>l.</hi> 3 <hi>r.</hi> Soul being. <hi>p.</hi> 62 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>r.</hi> 2. Abomination. <hi>p.</hi> 69 <hi>l.</hi> 12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeventh day. <hi>l.</hi> 21 <hi>r.</hi> ſeventh day. <hi>p.</hi> 70 <hi>l.</hi> 28 <hi>r.</hi> othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> means. <hi>p.</hi> 73. <hi>l.</hi> 32 <hi>r.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 75 <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> that manner <hi>l.</hi> 22 <hi>r.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 34. <hi>r.</hi> 3. He ought.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46814:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
